<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to children by James Kirkwood ...</title>
            <author>Kirkwood, James, 1650?-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15399</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12863272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12863272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94705</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94705)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 718:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to children by James Kirkwood ...</title>
                  <author>Kirkwood, James, 1650?-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition corrected and enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 153, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Tayler ..., and John Everingham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Children --  Conduct of life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:94705:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:94705:1"/>
                  <p>ADVICE TO CHILDREN.</p>
                  <p>BY <hi>James Kirkwood,</hi> Rector of <hi>Aſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> in
<hi>Bedfordſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Second Edition Corrected and Enlarged.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Tayler</hi> at the Ship
in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, and <hi>John Everingham</hi> at the Star in
<hi>Ludgate-Street,</hi> near the Weſt-End of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1693.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:94705:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94705:2"/>
                  <head>ADVICE TO CHILDREN.</head>
                  <div type="introduction">
                     <p>THERE is ſcarce any thing wherein all Nations, and Men of
all Religions, do more agree, than in the Common Duties of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their
Parents: Neither is there any thing that tends more to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and
happineſs, the beauty and ſtrength of Society, than for Children to perform
all thoſe Duties which they owe to their Parents. And yet how ſad is it to
think, that a great many Children, who have not only all the advantages which
Natural Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on affords, but likewiſe the aſſiſtance of Divine
Revelation, do nevertheleſs <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94705:3"/> carry themſelves in that
manner to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Parents, as if they either underſtood nothing of their
Duty, or were moſt prodigiouſly perverſe, and reſolved to <hi>rebel
againſt the Light,</hi> to trample upon all the Principles both of Natural
and Revealed Religion.</p>
                     <p>The Deſign of this ſhort Treatiſe is to ſhew what
the Duties of Children are towards their Parents, and to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt ſome
Conſiderations to excite them to do their Duty.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>1. Duty of Children, to honour their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: and how
they are to honour them.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Chlidren are bound to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their
Parents; which imports, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they ſhould entertain
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful and reverend thoughts of them, as being under God the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of
their Life and Being; they muſt not think ſlightingly, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluingly
of their Parents, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be their weakneſſes and Imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: They
ought to hate and abhor their Vices, every thing in them that is evil,
diſhonourable to God, and contrary to his Laws and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but ſtill
they ought to love <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94705:3"/> and honour their Perſons: And if at any
time diſreſpectful and irreverend thoughts ariſe in their minds, they
ought to check them, to accuſe and be angry with themſelves for them; and
to call to mind what God hath commanded them to do, when he ſaith, <hi>Honour
thy Father and thy Mother, that thy days may be long upon the Land which the
Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi> Ex. 20.12.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> This imports that they ought to expreſs
their inward Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and eſteem by all the outward marks and
demonſtrations thereof, in their Words and Deeds, their looks and geſtures;
theſe things are the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Mind, they ordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the
temper and diſpoſition thereof; ſo that if there be any thing of real
eſteem and regard towards any body in the heart, it will diſcover it ſelf
by ſome of thoſe outward expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. When <hi>Joſeph</hi> came
before his Father, with his two Sons, he did not omit the utmoſt reſpect,
tho' at that time <hi>Jacob</hi> was blind with Age, and could not ſee what
<hi>Joſeph</hi> did. The Text ſaith, <hi>He bowed himſelf with his Face
to the Earth,</hi> Gen. 48.12.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94705:4"/>We ſee likewiſe how <hi>Solomon</hi>
car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelf towards his Mother, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.19. <hi>Bathſheba
went unto King Solomon to ſpeak unto him for Adonijah: And the King roſe up
to meet her, and bowed himſelf unto her, and ſate down on his Throne, and
cauſed a ſeat to be ſet for the King's Mother, and ſhe ſate on his
right hand.</hi> Children are more apt to carry themſelves irreverently and
ſlightingly towards their Mother, which is the reaſon, as ſome think,
that ſhe is ſet down firſt, Lev. 19.3. <hi>Ye ſhall fear every Man his
Mother, and his Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This imports that they ought to cover the
infirmities and weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the imperfections and indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of
their Parents; to do as <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> did, <hi>Gen.</hi>
9.23. when <hi>Noah</hi> their Father was drunken, and was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered within
his Tent, <hi>They took a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and laid it upon both their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
and went backwards, and covered the nakedneſs of their Father, and their
faces were backward, and they ſaw not their Father's nakedneſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Bleſſings promiſed to <hi>Shem</hi> and
<hi>Japhet,</hi> and to their Poſterity, upon this <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94705:4"/>
occaſion, ſhew how acceptable what they did was unto God.</p>
                     <p>Children are not to publiſh the faults and follies of
their Parents; but ought to conceal them, all that they can. However, there are
two things very conſiſtent with this Duty: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may
and ought to do all that they can, by their private, modeſt, and humble
Advice, to reclaim their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents from their ſinful practices.
<hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> if they find it not ſo fit for them immediately to
adviſe their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; or if what they ſay hath not the deſigned effect,
then they may recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this charitable Office to the care of ſome other
body, who is a wiſe and kind, a pious and ſerious Friend, who may have
ſome more influence than themſelves towards the reclaiming their Parents.
This is the greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of true kindneſs, honour, and
reſpect to them, when their Chlidren ſincerely endeavour, in the
diſcreeteſt manner, to be the happy inſtruments of their Converſion and
Reformation, of turning them from Satan unto God: This is to be, in ſome
ſort, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Chriſt, to thoſe who are their Parents by Nature. O
how happy are <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94705:5"/> the Parents of ſuch worthy Children! How may
they rejoyce and bleſs God, who hath beſtowed on them ſo great a
Bleſſing?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Poverty of Parents does not exempt
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from this Duty.</note>As to the abovementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Inſtances of Honour
and Reſpect due from Children to their Parents, 'tis to be remembred, that no
alteration of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Eſtate and Circumſtances of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, does
exempt Children from their Obligation to pay them all manner of Reſpect. And
tho' Children be raiſed to greater Honours and Dignities than their Parents,
yet they muſt ſtill pay them all that regard and obſervance that is due
to the Authors of their Being. How great an Example of this Filial Reſpect,
was <hi>Joſeph:</hi> When he was raiſed to the greateſt Power and Honour
that the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> could confer upon him, yet ſtill he retained
a due Senſe of his Obligation to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his Aged Father, his Mother then
being Dead: He was not aſhamed to own him before <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> tho' his
Trade and Employment in the World was ſuch as was an Abomination to the
<hi>Egyptians.</hi> See, <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.31,32. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94705:5"/> And, <hi>Ch.</hi> 47.1,2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In like manner
we ſee that <hi>David,</hi> after he was A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed to be King, did not forget
his Duty towards his Poor Diſtreſſed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, he was not aſhamed to
own them before the King of <hi>Moab;</hi> he brought them before him, and
recommended them to him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.3,4.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt thoſe who diſhonour their
Parents.</note>If Children are thus obliged to Honour their Parents; what
ſhall be ſaid of thoſe who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, deſpiſe, and ſlight them,
all that ever they can; who undervalue them in their thoughts; who ſpeak of
them with great contempt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain; who ſpeak to them with great
inſolence; who mock and ſcorn them; who laugh at them, and make mouths at
them, and point at them with the finger; who reproach and revile them; who
break indecent jeſts upon them; who make them the Objects of their ſport
and paſtime; who take pleaſure in publiſhing their weakneſſes and
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretions, that others alſo may laugh at them, and deſpiſe them;
who, when their Parents grow old and poor,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> when themſelves come to have
more Wealth and Honour in the World <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94705:6"/> than their Parents have,
do thenceforth turn their backs upon their poor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, are aſhamed to own
them, and will not any longer take notice of them?</p>
                     <p>How dreadful and terrible are the Curſes and Judgments,
which God hath in ſtore againſt ſuch wretched Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? Deut. 27.16.
<hi>Curſed be he that ſetteth light by his Father or his Mother.</hi> Prov.
30.17. <hi>The Eye that mocketh at his Father, and deſpiſeth to obey his
Mother; the Ravens of the vallies ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles
ſhall eat it.</hi> That is, he who is a mocker and ſcorner of his Parents,
who deſpiſes and ſlights them, ſhall die a ſhameful death, and remain
unburied, and ſhall be expoſed to the Birds and Beaſts of prey, to be
eaten of them. It does not follow from hence, that all perverſe wretched
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren come to ſuch a ſhameful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely end: Only it ſhews what
oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times happeneth, and is very uſual, to wit, that ſuch mockers and
deſpiſers of Parents are puniſhed remarkably by the Juſtice of God in
this World, and are made Examples to all others, who will open their Eyes to
conſider the hand of God againſt ſuch ungodly Children.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94705:6"/>As for Inſtances of the Divine
Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt Mockers of Parents, all Ages and Countries are full of
them. <hi>Cham</hi> was made an Example of this, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.22,24,25.
<hi>And Cham the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Canaan ſaw the nakedneſs of his Father, and
told his two brethren without: And Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his
younger ſon had done unto him. And he ſaid, Curſed be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan; a
ſervant of ſervants ſhall he be unto his brethren.</hi> In which words,
the, <hi>Canaan</hi> the Son of <hi>Cham</hi> is only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, yet
<hi>Cham</hi> is not exempted from the Curſe; his puniſhment is hereby made
ſo much the greater, becauſe he is not only pronounced accurſed in his
own perſon (which is neceſſarily to be ſuppoſed, he having committed
the ſin which cauſed the Curſe) but alſo in his Poſterity, which
could not but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe mightily his grief, and make his puniſhment lye
more heavy upon him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ezekiel</hi> reckons this Sin, of contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and
diſhonouring Parents, as one great cauſe of the dreadful Judgments which
God inflicted upon the <hi>Jews, Ch.</hi> 22.7. <hi>In ye have they ſet Light
by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94705:7"/>
                     <head>2. Duty, to obey their Parents, and to hearken to their
Inſtructions.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Children are to obey their Parents, to do
what they bid them. See this in the Example of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when
<hi>Jacob</hi> ſent him to his Brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.13,14. <hi>And
Iſrael ſaid unto Joſeph, Do not thy brethren feed the flock in Shechem?
Come, and I will ſend thee unto them: And he ſaid to him, Here am I. And he
ſaid to him, Go, I pray thee, ſee whether it be well with thy brethren, and
well with the flocks, and bring me word again: ſo he ſent him out of the
vale of Hebron, and he came to Shechem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See likewiſe the Example of <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.17,
18,20. <hi>Jeſſe ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to David his Son, take now for thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren an
Ephah of this parched Corn, and theſe Ten Loaves, and run to the Camp to thy
Brethren: And carry theſe Ten Cheeſes unto the Captain of their Thouſand,
and look how thy Brethren fare, and take their pledge. And</hi> David
<hi>aroſe early in the Morning, and left the Sheep with a Keeper, and took,
and went as Jeſſe had Commanded him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94705:7"/>The Commands of Parents are either about
the ſame things which God hath commanded, or they are about things
indifferent, or about things unlawful. <hi>Firſt,</hi> if they are about the
ſame things which God hath commanded, they are ſo much the more to be
obeyed; as being the will and pleaſure both of their Father in Heaven, and of
their earthly Parents. In this caſe the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to obedience is double,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Children,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Obey your
Parents in the Lord, for this is right,</hi> that is, it is agreeable to all
Law, to the Law of God, of Nature, and of Nations; 'Tis that which is due to
the place of Parents; 'Tis their right to be obeyed by their Children.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> If their Parents Commands are about
things indifferent, that is, which are neither commanded, nor forbidden by God,
Children are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to obey them: God hath made it their Duty ſo to do,
<hi>Col.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren obey your Parents in all things; for this is
well pleaſing unto the Lord.</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Agreeable to this
was the Senſe of wiſe Heathens. <hi>See A. Gell. l. 2. c. 7.</hi>
                        </note>
This Obedience is very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him; he takes great pleaſure 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94705:8"/> and delight in it, to ſee thoſe obeyed and ſubmitted
to, whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be, as it were, in his own ſtead; whom he hath
cloathed with ſome beams of Divine Power; whom, with relation to their
Children, he hath made, in ſome ſenſe, ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; whoſe Will
ought to be a Law unto them, tho' only <hi>in the Lord.</hi> For,
<hi>Thirdly,</hi> if the thing commanded be plainly unlawful, they are to
refuſe compliance therewith; becauſe they are bound <hi>to obey God rather
than Man,</hi> rather than Father or Mother, rather than all the World: In this
caſe they ought to hearken to what our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26.
<hi>If any Man come to me, and hate not his Father, and Mother,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi> In which Words, Our Saviour is far from
encouraging Children to hate, or to diſobey their Parents; for we ſee how
zealouſly he vindicates the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Parents upon other occaſions. But
his Deſign, is, to teach Children, when the Will of God and the Will of their
Parents ſtand in Competition, that then they ought always to give the
preference to the Divine Will, and to chuſe rather to incur the
diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94705:8"/> of their Earthly Parents, than to offend
and provoke their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father. They ought to conſider, their Obligations
to God are much greater than to their Parents; he is the Maker both of them,
and of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; They live by his Bounty; the Earth they tread on is his;
the Air they breathe in, the Heavens that cover them, the Food they eat, the
Water they drink, the Garments that Cloath them, and all other things which
they enjoy for their benefit and comfort in the World, are the Lord's: He is
their great Maſter, who appoints them their buſineſs in the World, and
aſſures them of a reward; He alſo will reckon with them, and either
reward, or puniſh them, according to their Works; and therefore his Commands
are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to thoſe of all others.</p>
                     <p>But even in this caſe, Children are to expreſs, in their
very denial and refuſal of obedience, all that Honour and Reſpect to their
Parents, that's poſſible; that they may ſee it is not ſtubbornneſs,
but the fear of God, which makes them diſobey. By this means Parents may
perhaps be convinced, and made ſenſible of their Sin, and prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94705:9"/> with to ſhun thoſe evil things, which they ſee their
very Children do ſo much hate and abhor, and wherein they refuſe to
obey.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt ſtubborn and diſobedient
Children.</note>If Children are thus bound by the Laws of Heaven, to obey their
Parents; what ſhall be ſaid of thoſe, who make no account of their
Parents Commands, but ſet at naught all their Admonitions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels;
who will not follow their Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and be governed by them for their own
good; but do follow their own humour and fancy, and the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Cuſtoms
of others like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? They think themſelves too wiſe to need
Inſtruction, and are ready to ſay, That they ſhould do a great deal
better, if their Parents would let them alone, let them take their own way in
every thing, and never trouble their Heads about them. So little regard have
ſome to what their Parents ſay to them, That they have not patience to hear
them ſpeak, but run out of their preſence when they begin to talk
ſeriouſly to them; or if they are in an humour to hear them a little while,
yet they hear as if they heard not, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94705:9"/> they trample upon all
they ſay, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lay it to Heart. What a ſad mark is this of
approaching ruine, and of heavy Judgments, which hang over the heads of ſuch
ungodly Children, as you may ſee in the Sons of <hi>Ely,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
2.25. of whom it is ſaid, that <hi>they hearkened not unto the voice of their
Father, becauſe the Lord would ſlay them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ſtubborn Son was to be
put to death, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.18,19,20,21. <hi>If a man have a ſtubborn
and rebellious ſon, which will not obey the voice of his father, or the voice
of his mother, and that when they have chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, will not hearken unto
them: Then ſhall his father and mother lay hold on him, and bring him out
unto the Elders of his City, and unto the gate of his place: And they ſhall
ſay unto the Elders of his City, This our ſon is ſtubborn and
rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious, he will not obey our voice: He is a glutton and a drunkard. And
all the men of his City ſhall ſtone him with ſtones, that he die: ſo
ſhalt thou put evil away from among you, and all Iſrael ſhall hear and
fear.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In ancient times, in moſt Countries, Parents had an
abſolute power over <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94705:10"/> their Children, to puniſh them as
they thought good, for their diſobedience and other faults: And when
amongſt the <hi>Romans</hi> they leſſened this power, yet they did it at
firſt only in part; The Father was enjoyned to preſent his diſobedient
Child to the Judge, that he might be puniſhed; and the Judge was to pronounce
ſuch a Sentence as the Father thought fit. This came ſomewhat near the Law
of <hi>Moſes.</hi> By which it appears, what the ſenſe of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind was
concerning the exceeding greatneſs of the crime of ſtubbornneſs and
diſobedience in Children to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <head>3. Duty of Children, to be Faithful to their Parents, and
not to diſpoſe of their Goods without their Conſent.</head>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">3. Duty, to be Faithful to their
Parents, and not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of their Goods without their
conſent.</note>3dly. They ought Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſerve their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to be
careful to promote their Temporal Welfare and Happineſs, and to be as
uſeful and helpful to them in their Worldly Concerns, as is poſſible. Not
only Duty, but Intereſt <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94705:10"/> ſhould excite Children to do
this; for, their Happineſs and Proſperity does in great meaſure depend
upon that of their Parents. 'Tis not often that Children thrive and flouriſh
in the World, when their Parents are reduced to Miſery and Poverty. And
therefore, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to their own Intereſt and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ought to make them
careful to do their Parents the beſt Service that is in their power.</p>
                     <p>But beſides this, Gratitude ought to prevail with
Children, faithfully to ſerve their Parents, and to be uſeful to them, ſo
far as they can. Are Parents the Authors of their Life and Being? Have they
nouriſhed and ſuſtained them for ſo many Years? Have they been at ſo
much pains and coſt, and endured ſo much pain and travel to bring them up,
and to make them ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to do ſome Service in the World? And ſhall not
they reckon it their Happineſs and Honour, to have an opportunity to ſerve
them, and to be helpful to them, and by their care and pains, and
faithfulneſs towards them, to witneſs a due ſenſe of Gratitude, for all
that they not only have done, but endured alſo for them, and that 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94705:11"/> for a great many Years, when they could not do any thing
for themſelves? The conſideration of theſe things, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be of
great force with all Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous minds.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful and treacherous
Children.</note>But, alas! How far are a great many Children from doing this
Duty to their Parents? Inſtead of doing them faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, they prove
falſe and treacherous to them; inſtead of being careful of thoſe things
they entruſt them with, they cheat and deceive them; they rob them; they
diſpoſe of their Goods without their knowledge and approbation; they make
uſe of them to ſerve their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Folly, and to gratifie their Wild
and Youthful Inclinations: Yea, and how apt are ſome, to glory in this, as if
they had done a very brave and worthy action, when they have had the good
Fortune, as they reckon it, to defraud their poor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents?</p>
                     <p>As Children, when they are diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to rob their
Parents, are of all Thieves the moſt dangerous, being in their Parents
Boſom, and thereby ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving opportunity to cheat them the <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94705:11"/>
more ſucceſsfully; ſo their crime is the moſt heinous in its kind, 'tis
attended with very aggravating Circumſtances; 'tis ſo great, that there is
no name bad enough to expreſs it by, and to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it in all its
deformity. How ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible was <hi>Jacob</hi> of this, when he was purſued
by <hi>Laban</hi> his unrighteous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-Law, and accuſed by him of
having ſtoln his Idols? <hi>With whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</hi> ſays he to <hi>Laban,
thou findeſt them, let him not live,</hi> Gen. 31.32. We ſee what a
ſevere Cenſure the wiſe Man paſſeth on ſuch Perſons,
<hi>Prov.</hi> 28.24. <hi>Whoſo robbeth his Father and his Mother, and
ſaith, It is no Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſame is a Companion of a
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer;</hi> that is, he is to be look'd on, as no better than one of
thoſe who rob and murder on the High-Way, as a Man deſperately wicked, who
is diſpoſed to act any ſort of Villany and Impiety, who will ſtick at
nothing in purſuit of his mad and wretched de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that may gratifie his
Luſts and Paſſions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:94705:12"/>
                     <head>4. Duty of Children, to be determined by their Parents as
to their Calling.</head>
                     <p n="4">4thly. They are to be determined by them, as to their
Calling and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, if it be an honeſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful one. Their Parents
are to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ordinarily more wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to chuſe for
them, than they are to chuſe a Trade for themſelves: They have more
experience, and know the World better than their Children do; and no doubt,
they have kindneſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for them to wiſh them well, and to deſign
their advantage, and not to preſs them to any Trade or way of Life, which
they believe is inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and like to be hurtful to them: But if Parents
ſhould be miſtaken, as to the fitneſs of the Employment, to which they
deſign their Children; and ſuppoſing the Children to be ſenſible of
the great inconveniences thereof, which the Parents, through prejudices and
partialities, do not ſee; in this caſe Children may, with all due
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, meekneſs, and humility, repreſent to their Parents what their
thoughts are, and tell them what objections they <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94705:12"/> have
againſt ſuch a Calling; that their Parents may be prevailed upon, by their
Reaſons, to alter their reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: or if they be not ſo fit
themſelves to diſcourſe their Parents upon ſuch a ſubject, they may
do it by ſome wiſe and diſcreet Friends. And if, after all, Parents be
wilful in their intention and deſign; Children are not, upon the account of
uncertain, or proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inconveniences, to oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Will
of their Parents; they ought to ſubmit themſelves to their Judgment, if the
Trade, or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Life, to which they deſign them, be not diſhoneſt
and unlawful; for then there is no farther queſtion to be made; the caſe is
clear: The Will of God is always to be preferred to the Will of Man. <hi>He
that loveth Father or Mother more than me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>is not
worthy of me,</hi> Matth. 10.37. But if there be nothing of diſhoneſty or
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs in ſuch an Employment, they are to enter upon it with all the
chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs that's poſſible; leaving all events unto God. It will
afford great peace and comfort to their minds, whatever afterwards falls out,
when they conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they did what was their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94705:13"/>
to do; they ſubmitted their own opinion to the Judgment of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
whom God hath commanded them to obey. Whatever may be their temporal loſs,
they are ſure of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual gain. God will plentifully reward their humble
obedience, and ready com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Will of their earthly Parents.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this
Duty.</note>From what hath been ſaid on this Head, we may ſee how much they
are to be blamed, who are ſo far from being determined by their Parents, in
the way and manner of their living in the World, that they either wholly give
up themſelves to idleneſs, and waſte their time in vain and fooliſh
Company; or they chuſe ſome way of living, that is either diſhoneſt, or
very inconvenient for them in many regards; or if they comply with their
Parents, ſo far as to enter upon ſome honeſt way of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, yet they do
not keep at it, but leave it, and become Prodigals; they ſpend their
ſubſtance in riotous living; they waſte and conſume what their Parents
beſtow upon them, in drinking, gaming, and whoring, and ſuch like
extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94705:13"/> whereby as they occaſion a great deal
of ſorrow and grief to their Parents, ſo they bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
ſudden Deſtruction.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>5. Duty, not to ſuffer themſelves to be beſtowed in
Marriage againſt their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Will.</head>
                     <p n="5">5thly. As to their Marriage, they are not to ſuffer
themſelves to be beſtowed, without their Parents conſent, in whom there
is a right inveſted to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of their Children in Marriage in due
time, as appears from <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.3. <hi>Neither ſhalt thou make
Marriages with them:</hi> (to wit, with the ſeven Nations of <hi>Canaan</hi>)
<hi>Thy Daughter thou ſhalt not give unto his Son; nor his Daughter
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>alt thou take unto thy Son.</hi>
And, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.36,37,38. the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> does very
poſitively aſſert this power of Parents, to diſpoſe of their
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Marriage, when they ſee it fit and needful ſo to do.</p>
                     <p>We ſee how dutifully <hi>Samſon</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelf
towards his Parents in this matter, <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.1,2. <hi>And</hi>
Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>went down to</hi> Timnath, <hi>and ſaw a Woman in</hi> Timnath,
<hi>and he came up and <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94705:14"/> told his Father and his Mother, and
ſaid, I have ſeen a Woman in</hi> Timnath <hi>of the Daughters of the
Philiſtins, now therefore get her for me to Wife.</hi> We ſee what
<hi>Iſaac</hi> gave his Son <hi>Jacob</hi> in charge, when he was to go to
<hi>Haran,</hi> Gen. 28.1,2. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take a Wife of the Daughters
of</hi> Canaan: <hi>Ariſe, go to</hi> Padan-Aram, <hi>to the Houſe of</hi>
Bethuel <hi>thy Mother's Father, and take thee a Wife from thence of the
Daughters of</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban, <hi>thy Mother's Brother.</hi> In like manner
<hi>Abraham</hi> directs his Servant what Wife to chuſe for his Son
<hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> Gen. 24.3,4. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take a Wife unto my Son
of the Daughters of the</hi> Canaanites, <hi>but thou ſhalt go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my
Country, and unto my Kindred, and take a Wife unto my Son</hi> Iſaac. And of
<hi>Iſhmael</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.21. That <hi>his Mother,</hi>
Hagar, <hi>took him a Wife.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How very juſt and reaſonable is it, that they who are
under God, the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their life and being in the World, whoſe Goods
and Poſſeſſion Children are, ſhould be acknowledged and advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
with by them, and depended on in the ſettling of themſelves in the World,
in ſuch a ſtate of Life, which <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94705:14"/> will prove either the
foundation of great happineſs or of great miſery? To give themſelves
away, without their Parents Conſent, is a kind of theft; it is to invade the
right of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; to rob them of that which God hath given them; for, Children
are not their own, they are the Goods and Poſſeſſion of Parents, to
whom God hath given them as an <hi>Inheritance, Pſal.</hi> 127.3. and
therefore Children have no more power to diſpoſe of themſelves, than to
diſpoſe of their Parents Goods without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
                     <p>We ſee how great the Power of Parents was, by the Law of
<hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 30.3,4,5. To diſanul the raſh Vows of their
Children before Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. <hi>If a Woman alſo vow a Vow unto the Lord, and
bind her ſelf by a Bond, being in her Father's Houſe, in her youth, and her
Father hear her Vow and her Bond, wherewith ſhe hath bound her Soul, and her
Father ſhall hold his peace at her: Then all her Vows ſhall ſtand, and
every Bond wherewith ſhe hath bound her Soul, ſhall ſtand: But if her
Father diſallow her in the day that he heareth; not any of her Vows, or of
her <pb n="26" facs="tcp:94705:15"/> Bonds, wherewith ſhe hath bound her Soul, ſhall
ſtand: And the Lord ſhall forgive her, becauſe her Father diſallowed
her.</hi> Now if it be thus in a Father's power, to diſanul his Daughter's
raſh Vow which ſhe made to God, how much more may we reckon it in his
Power, to diſanul her raſh and indiſcreet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to Man, of
beſtowing her ſelf without her Parents allowance? Can there be any thing
more unjuſt, more unkind, more unthankful, and more unnatural, than for
Children, who have been brought up, nouriſhed, and cheriſhed by their
Parents, for whom all their care and pains have been beſtowed, to diſpoſe
of themſelves in the moſt important affair of their lives, without their
knowledge, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Will? What a grief and trouble of heart muſt
this needs be to their poor Parents? As we ſee it was to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and
<hi>Rebekah, Gen.</hi> 26.34,35. <hi>And</hi> Eſau <hi>was forty years old
when he took to Wife</hi> Judith, <hi>the daughter of</hi> Beeri <hi>the</hi>
Hittite, <hi>and</hi> Baſhemath, <hi>the daughter of</hi> Elon <hi>the</hi>
Hittite, <hi>which were a grief of mind to</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and to</hi>
Rebekah. As to ſuch undutiful Children, who do thus beſtow themſelves
againſt their <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94705:15"/> Parents will and conſent, it is very
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, that they ſeldom live hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily and comfortably; they bring upon
themſelves very often a great deal of ſorrow and trouble, laſting
Miſery and Woe: They live to eat the fruit of their fooliſh doings; and
wiſh, when it is to little purpoſe, that they had never done ſo mad and
wicked a thing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <head>6. Duty, to ſubmit to their Parents Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs and
Chaſtenings.</head>
                     <p n="6">6thly. They are meekly and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to ſubmit to
their Reproofs, to their Chaſtenings and Corrections. It is a Power that God
hath given Parents over their Children, to correct and chaſten them for their
Faults: This is neceſſary for Childrens good; and therefore, when Parents
do correct them, they ought not to be angry with them, or grumble at their
ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which they uſe for reforming of them; much leſs are they to
reſiſt and rebel againſt them. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. <hi>We have had
Fathers of our fleſh, which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected us, and we gave them Reverence.</hi> 
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94705:16"/> Yea, tho' Parents ſometimes exceed the bounds of
Prudence and Diſcretion in chaſtiſing their Children, tho' they indulge a
little to their own Paſſion; yet Children are bound patiently to bear and
ſuffer their Corrections: They are not to fly out into indecent and
irreverent words and actions, but with all the ſubmiſſion and reſpect
that's poſſible, ought to endeavour to miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the wrath and paſſion
of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Parents; and afterwards they are to ſtudy all that ever they
can, to prevent their anger and diſpleaſure, by a moſt humble, reverend,
and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful carriage.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Children.</note>How
much may this ſerve to reprove thoſe, who are ſo far from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in good
part their Parents correcting and chaſtening of them, that they refuſe to
ſubmit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? They reſiſt them, and rebel againſt them. Can there be
any thing more unnatural and monſtrous, than to ſee thoſe who owe their
being to their Parents; who have been brought up by them; who have met with
ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny teſtimonies of a tender care, and <pb n="29" facs="tcp:94705:16"/> of great
kindneſs; to riſe up againſt them? To fly into the faces of thoſe who
are the Authors of their being? to lift up their hand againſt them? This is a
Sin of ſo crying a Nature, that he who was guilty thereof, was to be put to
Death, by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 21.15. <hi>He that ſmiteth his
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or his Mother, ſhall be ſurely put to Death.</hi> So ſenſible
were ſome amongſt the very Heathens of the greatneſs of this Sin, that to
ſhew their abhorrence of it, they were wont to puniſh thoſe who were
Guilty of it, in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manner; They ſewed them in a Sack with a Dog,
Cat, Viper and Ape, and ſo drown'd them all together. Hereby they
ſingnified, that ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were not any longer to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men,
or the Children of Men, but were to be reckoned with the vileſt and
baſeſt of Beaſts and Vermine, and in that Quality were to be caſt out
of the ſight of all living.</p>
                     <p>How greatly does it aggravate this Sin, when Children have
met with no ſevere, nor unmerciful dealing from their Parents? But have been
treated by them, with all that gentleneſs and <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94705:17"/> kindneſs
that was poſſible. And yet for ſuch Children to riſe up againſt their
Parents, is a Crime of ſo black a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that it is no wonder if the hand
of God appear againſt them for it, in a very ſignal manner; as it did in
the caſe of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> for whom his Father <hi>David</hi> had ſo
great a fondneſs: This unthankful and unnatural Son roſe up againſt him,
and endeavoured by force and violence to pull him from the Throne, and to
uſurp the Royal Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. See how the hand of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared againſt him, 2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 18.9. <hi>And</hi> Abſalom <hi>met the Servants of</hi> David;
<hi>and</hi> Abſalom <hi>rode upon a Mule, and the Mule went under the thick
Boughs of a great Oak, and his Head caught hold of the Oak, and he was taken up
between the Heaven and the Earth, and the Mule that was under him went
away.</hi> And, ver. 14. it is ſaid, that Joab <hi>took three darts in his
hand, and thruſt them through the heart of</hi> Abſalom, <hi>while he was
yet alive in the midſt of the Oak.</hi> And, ver. 15. <hi>Ten young Men that
bare</hi> Joab's <hi>Armour, compaſſed about, and ſmote</hi> Abſalom,
<hi>and ſlew him.</hi> And, ver. 17. <hi>They took</hi> Abſalom <hi>and
caſt him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a great Pit in the Wood, and laid a very great heap of Stones
upon him.</hi> This <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94705:17"/> was done as a laſting Monument of
<hi>Abſalom</hi>'s ſin and ſhame, and of God's righteous Judgment upon
him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>7. Duty, to love their Parents, and how they are to
expreſs their Love.</head>
                     <p n="7">7thly, Children ought to love their Parents; and to
expreſs it by all thoſe Offices, which are in their Power to do for them;
by ſerving them readily; by ſtudying ways how to make them well pleaſed:
by ſympathizing with them in all their troubles; by aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them,
and doing all they can to make their Lives joyful and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; by
ſhunning every thing that may grieve them, or make them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie: They
ought to refuſe no labour, nor pains to do them ſervice, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when
they are ſick and weak, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with the Burden of Old Age, or poor
and indigent, under any ſort of neceſſity whatſoever; then ought
Children to be very ready to help them, to comfort and to encourage them, to do
what in them lies to make their lives eaſie to them, and to ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their
Burdens. This is called, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4. <hi>A ſhewing Piety at
home.</hi> It is an act of Religion and Worſhip, which <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94705:18"/>
God is well pleaſed with. We ſee how <hi>Joſeph</hi> nouriſhed his
Father and his Brethren, and all his Fathers Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with Bread,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 47.12. How worthy of Praiſe was that Excellent Moabiteſs
<hi>Ruth,</hi> who not only gleaned for her poor Mother-in-Law <hi>Naomi,</hi>
but did alſo, when Food was given her by <hi>Boaz</hi> for her own
Refreſhment, reſerve part of it, and give it to her Mother. See
<hi>Ruth</hi> 2.18.</p>
                     <p>It was an old Roman Law<note n="*" place="margin">Senec.
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. l. 1. Cont. 1.7. and 19.</note>. <hi>Let Children re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their
Parents or be put in Priſon.</hi> Which ſheweth what was the Senſe of
that wiſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, concerning this Important Duty of Children towards their
Parents; they lookt upon them as unworthy of Liberty to converſe amongſt
Men, and to enjoy the common Priviledges of Society, who were ſo far void of
Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, as not to relieve and aſſiſt their poor Parents. 'Twas
likewiſe an Athenian Law, 
<note n="*" place="margin">Diog. Laert. in Solone.</note>That
<hi>if any did not relieve their Parents, they ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd baſe
and ignoble.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How many Examples have there been amongſt the Heathens, of
Eminent Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94705:18"/> towards Parents? Such was that Act of
her,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Valer. Max.</hi> l. 5. Cap. 4.</note> who when her
Old Father was condemned to be put to Death in Priſon, viſited him often,
and gave him ſuck, and ſo preſerved him alive, who otherwiſe muſt
have dyed of Famine.</p>
                     <p>The like inſtance we meet with in the ſame Author,<note place="margin">Valer. Max. ibid.</note> of a worthy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Daughter, who did in
the ſame manner preſerve her Mother in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, being Condemned to dye.
When the Keeper of the Priſon, to whom the charge of putting her to Death was
committed, found after ſome time, that her Daughter kept her alive by giving
her ſuck, he was ſo affected with the greatneſs of the Daughter's
Compaſſion and Tenderneſs to her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he made it known to
thoſe in Power, who were likewiſe ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily touched with ſuch an
unuſual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of tender Affection; that they pardoned the Mother, as
the greateſt Reward they could beſtow on the Daughter for her marvellous
Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94705:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94705:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:94705:20"/>What can there be more juſt and
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, than for Children thus to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to requite their Parents,
for their great care and kindneſs towards them, when they were not able to
help themſelves? The time was, when their Parents were as Eyes, and Hands,
and Feet to them; they did every thing for them, they not being capable to do
any thing for themſelves: How ready therefore ſhould they be to ſerve
their Parents, to aſſiſt them by all good Offices, when their condition
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it?</p>
                     <p>This is a Duty to which Children are ſo ſtrictly
obliged, (to wit, <hi>the aſſiſting and relieving of their Parents</hi>)
that no pretence is ſufficient to abſolve them from the Obligation thereof.
The <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> thought they had found out an Exception from this
Rule, which was this; that if Children gave away their Wealth to Pious and
Charitable uſes, they were freed from the Obligation of relieving their
Parents: They taught them in this caſe, to tell their Parents, <hi>It is
Corban, that is to ſay, a Gift, by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou mighteſt be profited
by me,</hi> Mar. 7.11. And by ſaying this, they made People believe, that
they were <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94705:20"/> ſufficiently freed from all Obligations to
take care of, and provide for their Parents. But our Saviour reproves them
ſeverely, telling them, that this was no other than the <hi>making void the
Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God by their Traditions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt unkind and unnatural
Children.</note>We may ſee from this, what Judgment to make of ſuch unkind,
undutiful, and unnatural Children, who do wholly neglect their Parents,
eſpecially in their old Age, and in their poor and low Eſtate; who ſhew
them no more pity, and expreſs no more love nor tenderneſs towards them,
than if they were not their Parents; who grudge them the leaſt ſupply; and
take all the wicked courſes that they can, to ſtarve them to death, that
they may be rid of them; who wiſh and long for, and rejoyce in the Death of
their poor Parents. O what a horrid Barbarity and Inhumanity is this! Shall not
many Pagans riſe up in Judgment againſt ſuch Children, and Condemn them?
How little do they deſerve the Name of, <hi>Chriſtian Children?</hi> Their
true Name is, <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian,</hi> and <hi>unnatural Children.</hi> As
<hi>Solomon</hi> bid the Sluggard, <hi>go to the Ant;</hi> ſo may we bid
ſuch hard-hearted and <pb n="36" facs="tcp:94705:21"/> unmerciful Children, <hi>go to the
Stork,</hi> of whom it is told, 
<note n="*" place="margin">S. Baſil. in Hexaemer. Homil. 8.
Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. Hexaem. l. 5. c. 16.</note>that when the old Dams can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not feed
themſelves, their little ones feed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them; when their Feathers
fall from them, they cover them with their Feathers; and when they are not able
to fly, they couple themſelves together, to carry them upon their Backs. Let
<hi>uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Children</hi> go to this <hi>compaſſionate
Creature,</hi> and conſider her ways and be wiſe; Let them learn from her,
to be more kind and affectionate, and tender-hearted towards their Parents, and
not any longer to harden their Bowels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>8. Duty, to pray for their Parents.</head>
                     <p n="8">8thly, Becauſe all that Children can do is not
ſufficient to requite the Love and tender care of their Parents; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they ought to pray to God, that he would reward them, and preſerve them, and
keep them alive; that he would ſupply all their wants, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them in
all their troubles, and requite their Love, their tender care, 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94705:21"/> and their great coſt and pains they have been at to
bring them up, and to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them. How happy are the Parents of ſuch
Children, who are ſupplicants and interceſſors, at the Throne of Grace,
for good things unto them? Such Children are the ſtrength of their Parents;
they are a great bleſſing unto them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note>If it be the Duty of Children, thus to pray to God, in behalf
of their Parents; what ſhall we ſay of thoſe, who neither pray for them,
nor themſelves, but live like the Beaſts that periſh, and mind nothing
that's good? And if their Crime is great, who do not at all pray for their
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; how dreadful is their Guilt, who Curſe them? What dreadful
Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may ſuch Monſters of wickedneſs expect? <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.20.
<hi>Who ſo Curſeth his Father or his Mother, his Lamp ſhall be put out in
obſcure darkneſs;</hi> that is, he ſhall be reduced unto a ſad,
afflicted, and miſerable State; his proſperous condition (which is compared
to Light, or to a Lamp) ſhall be turned into Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity and Miſery, and
that very great, which is expreſſed by <hi>[obſcure Darkneſs,]</hi> 
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:94705:22"/> he ſhall be made very miſerable; his ſtate and
condition in the World ſhall become moſt uncomfortable; as it is for a Man
who walketh in a way that is full of Light, where he beholds a great many
Objects, which afford him plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight, ſuddenly to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived
of all this, and to find himſelf all alone in obſcure Darkneſs, without
all help and comfort. By the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſuch ungodly and
unnatural Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were without any pardon to be put to death. <hi>Exod.</hi>
21.17. <hi>He that Curſeth his Father or his Mother, ſhall ſurely be put
to Death.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Duties of Children towards their deceaſed
Parents.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Duties of Children to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Parents.</note>Beſides the Duties which Children owe their
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents whilſt they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, there are ſome things likewiſe for them
to do after their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe; Particularly,</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. Duty, they ought to bury them
decently.</note>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> They ought to bury them decently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to their Quality, ſo far as the preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of their Eſtate
will permit: <pb n="39" facs="tcp:94705:22"/> They ought on the one hand to avoid whatever
looks like Baſeneſs and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and which is not, in ſome
meaſure, anſwerable to their Parents Eſtate and Place while they lived;
and on the other hand, they ought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void an over-laviſh Sumptuouſneſs,
they muſt do nothing above their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, or above their Rank and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.
A great many, out of a vain and fooliſh humour of Solemnizing their Parents
Funerals in a ſumptuous and ſplendid manner, have ſo far weakened their
Eſtate, as ſcarce ever to be able to recover themſelves again. Children
therefore ought, in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to govern themſelves, by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and
Example of Prudent and Diſcreet Perſons of their own Rank, in the World;
but eſpecially, they are herein to govern themſelves by the Will of the
Dead, ſo far as it was made known to them or others: Thus, we ſee,
<hi>Joſeph</hi> and his Brethren did to their Father <hi>Jacob</hi> when he
died; he charged them to Bury him with his Fathers, in the Cave that is in the
Field of <hi>Ephron</hi> the <hi>Hittite, Gen.</hi> 49.29. And accordingly his
Sons did as he commanded them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.12,13.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:94705:23"/>
                        <note place="margin">2. Duty, to
fulfil their laſt Will.</note>2dly. They are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to ſhew the
greateſt readineſs that is poſſible, to Obey their Parents in every
other thing which by their laſt Will they appointed and Ordered to be done;
for Example, the Payment of Debts and Legacies, the giving ſo much Money for
ſome Excellent and Pious Deſign, or for the Relief of ſome Perſons in
Diſtreſs and Want, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Will of the Dead has, in all Ages, and amongſt all
People, been reckoned a thing moſt Sacred and Inviolable: Now, if the Will of
the Deceaſed be Obligatory unto any, it muſt certainly be ſo in a
ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to Children, whom both the Laws of Natural and Revealed
Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>to Obey their Parents in all things.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">3. Duty, to call to mind their good
Advices, and to follow their good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note>3dly. They ought to call to
mind often their Parents good Advices, and to follow their Pious Examples. If
whilſt they were alive, they neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or, at leaſt, did not obſerve,
ſo well as they ſhould have <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94705:23"/> done, their Admonitions
and Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and did not make very great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their good
Examples; they ought (now they are gone from them, and to return to them no
more) to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be ſo much the more careful to follow their uſeful
Directions and Examples. There is no ſuch way as this, to keep the Memory of
Parents freſh and green. There can no Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be erected comparable to
this, when Children imitate their Parents Virtue and Piety. The good Kings
which came of the Stock and Lineage of <hi>David,</hi> made the Memory of their
Father <hi>David</hi> to be ſtill ſweet and flouriſhing, when his Body
was rotten in the Grave. Thus 'tis ſaid of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> 1
<hi>King.</hi> 3.3. <hi>He walked in the Statutes of</hi> David <hi>his
Father.</hi> And of <hi>Aſa,</hi> it is ſaid, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.11.
<hi>And</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa <hi>did that which was right in the Eyes of the Lord, as
did</hi> David <hi>his Father.</hi> And of <hi>Joſiah</hi> it is written, 2
<hi>King.</hi> 22.2. <hi>He did that which was right in the ſight of the
Lord, and walked in all the ways of</hi> David <hi>his Father, and turned not
aſide to the right hand, or to the left.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:94705:24"/>'Twill be an Act of Juſtice, as well
as a Teſtimony of due Reſpect and Love to your Deceaſed Parents, now and
then to make Honourable mention of them, to talk of their good Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, their
uſeful Sayings, and their good Cuſtoms and Examples. But this is not to be
done too often, nor in all Companies; only amongſt thoſe who will bear it,
and at ſuch times when it is moſt likely to do good.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">4. Duty, to do what they can
Lawfully to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs evil Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports concerning them.</note>4thly. They
ought to do all that they can Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, in a calm and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent manner, to
ſuppreſs evil Reports, which are ſpread abroad of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents after
their Deceaſe. The Credit and Honour of Parents ought to be very dear to
Children: And therefore, when their good Name is wounded, and when they, by
Death, are incapable to vindicate themſelves, 'tis the Duty of Children, who
are, as it were, their living Images, to do their utmoſt to preſerve their
Name from injurious Reports. If what is ſaid of them be manifeſtly falſe,
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought to make known the naked <pb n="43" facs="tcp:94705:24"/> truth, ſo far as
is fit; which will be the beſt and ſureſt Vindication. But if what is
ſaid againſt their Parents be true, and of that Nature as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no
excuſe or extenuation, the beſt thing that Children can do in ſuch a
caſe, is, to avoid ſuch wicked things themſelves as their Parents were
Guilty of. They who follow the Evil Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Parents, cauſe them to
ſtink more and more. The poſterity of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> who followed his
wretched Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, made his Evil Name to be the more remembred, and cauſed
this blur to continue in his Character, from one Age to another, <hi>Jeroboam
which made Iſrael to Sin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">5. Duty, to retain a firm
kindneſs for their Friends.</note>5thly. They ought to retain a ſincere and
firm kindneſs and eſteem, for all thoſe who witneſſed a true and
conſtant Chriſtian Friendſhip to their Parents, who were always faithful
to them, ready to ſerve them, and to do them all good Offices, according to
their ability: Such Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, it may be very reaſonably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, will
not be treacherous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful to the Children, who have te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified a
laſting and faithful Friendſhip <pb n="44" facs="tcp:94705:25"/> to the Parents.
<hi>Thy own Friend,</hi> ſaith Solomon, <hi>and thy Father's Friend,
forſake not,</hi> Prov. 27.10.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Againſt Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect theſe
Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note>Now, if it be the Duty of Children, to expreſs their Love and
Regard towards their deceaſed Parents, in the abovemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned manner, what
ſhall be ſaid of thoſe who run a courſe quite contrary to all this? No
ſooner are their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents dead, but they begin to rejoyce and triumph, and to
bleſs themſelves, that at laſt they are delivered from thoſe
reſtraints they were formerly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that now they have the liberty to
give themſelves the ſwing, and to gratifie every Luſt and Paſſion, as
much as ever they can. As to their Parents <hi>Will,</hi> they take no care to
fulfill it; henceforth they know no other <hi>Will</hi> but their own; as to
that of their Parents, they think they had too much to do with it, when they
were alive, and now that they are dead, they reckon themſelves abſolved
from all Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them. As to their Debts and Legacies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
They make no Conſcience to pay them, unleſs a neceſſity of
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the Laws force them to do <pb n="45" facs="tcp:94705:25"/> their Duty. As
to the Credit and good Name of their Parents, ſo little regard have they
thereto, as to be ready to give ear to thoſe who ſpeak ill of them; yea
themſelves are apt to blaze abroad ſuch things as tend to their Reproach
and Diſparagement. As to their Advices and Admonitions, they laugh at them,
they look on them as fit only to be liſt'ned to by melancholly dull Souls,
who have no reliſh of Manly Pleaſures: They have no mind to be interrupted
in their Mirth and Jollity, and therefore farewell any Advice or Council that
looks like ſerious. As to their Example, they ſlight and deſpiſe it;
they look on themſelves as too wiſe to be led either by Precept or Example,
but according as they ſuit their own Humour and Inclination. As to their
Parents Friends, they turn their Backs upon them, they break off all
Correſpondence with them, and keep them at the greateſt diſtance, as if
they were afraid of them; they know that they are of the ſame Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and
Principles with their Parents, and therefore they cannot endure them, for fear
of being told by them ſome thing or other, that does not agree 
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94705:26"/> with their vain and wicked Practices, and with their
raſh and fooliſh Deſigns. In a word, they ſtudy a perfect Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
to their Parents in all things; they pull down whatever they built, they root
up whatever they planted, they hate what they loved, and love whatever they
hated. So unlike do they render themſelves to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in all their
Manners and Cuſtoms, that all who ſee them muſt needs call them a
degenerate Seed, Curſed Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, unnatural Plants, ready to be hewn down
and caſt into the Fire.</p>
                     <p>From what hath been ſaid, Children may ſee what their
Duty is, which they owe to their Parents; which that they may perform, there
are ſeveral things which ſerve as powerful Motives and Arguments to excite
them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Motives to excite Children to do theſe things.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1 Motive, from the divine
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</note>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> It will tend migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to move them to
<hi>Honour their Father and Mother,</hi> if they conſider who requires this
at their hands. This Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth not from Men, but from God; 
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94705:26"/> It is a Law made by him who is their Maker; and therefore
by right of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation may require their Obedience: It is a Law made by their
faithful pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, and rich provider; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by Virtue of his daily
care over them, and kindneſs to them, may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them what he thinks good:
This is the will of their Father in Heaven, of their Lord and King, of him who
will call them to an account, <hi>and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to them according to their
Works;</hi> of him who is their greateſt and beſt Friend, if they do his
Will and keep his Commandments; but will be their moſt dreadful and terrible
Enemy, if they do not obey his Voice: If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Children have any ſenſe
of God on their Souls; If they conſider his infinite greatneſs, Power,
Wiſdom, Juſtice, Truth, Faithfulneſs, Mercy, and Kindneſs; they cannot
but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perform what he requires, when once they know what is his
holy will and pleaſure. Now, as to what I ſpeak of, to wit the Duty of
Children to Parents, it is plain and clear, not only from thoſe Laws which
are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Holy Scripture, which were revealed from Heaven to Holy Men, 
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94705:27"/> whom God made uſe of to be the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhers thereof to
the World; but likewiſe from the Laws of Nature, thoſe clear
impreſſions which God hath made on the Minds of Men in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in
all Ages; whereby they are taught that Children ought to honour and obey their
Parents, to love them and to relieve them, and provide for them, if they
ſtand in need of their help<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicius</hi>
upon E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pictet. Cap. <hi>37.</hi> and <hi>Arrianus l. 2. c. 10.</hi>
                        </note>.
Theſe have always been the calm and ſober thoughts of all Men; and when any
were ſo wicked as to violate this ſacred Law, they were hated and abhorred
by all others; and in all well govern'd States, were puniſhed according to
the demerits of their Crime, and the degree of their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and
perverſeneſs, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by the Parents, or by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Judges,
upon complaint made by Parents. The Senſe of all this ought to move Children
to honour their Father and Mother, that they may approve themſelves to God,
who requires them to do ſo, and that upon the ſevereſt Penalties, if they
ſhall dare to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them, and diſobey them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:94705:27"/>
                        <note place="margin">2. Motive, from the
Divine Promiſe.</note>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> To encourage Children to perform
their Duty to their Parents, God hath been pleaſed to add a gracious
promiſe. <hi>That thy days may be long</hi>
                        <note n="†" place="margin">Or, that they, i. e. Thy Parents, may prolong thy days, <hi>to
wit, by their Prayers and Bleſſing.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>upon the Land which the
Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi> He might only have commanded them to do this, by
Virtue of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Power and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Authority, which he has over all
Men, without propoſing any Reward; but ſuch is his infinite Bounty and
Goodneſs, that he hath added a Promiſe to the Command, thereby to make
Childrens Duty the more eaſie.</p>
                     <p>As to the Promiſe it ſelf, it is not to be underſtood
abſolutely, as if all good Children ſhould live long; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of
Temporal Bleſſings are made conditionally, that is, ſo far as God ſees
ſuch things beſt and fitteſt for us: So that as to this promiſe of long
life. God will beſtow it, if it be moſt for his own Glory, and the good and
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Children. Oftentimes he does lengthen out the years of pious and
dutiful Children; whereas the years of <pb n="50" facs="tcp:94705:28"/> wicked and
undutiful Children are ſhortned by their prophane and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed courſes; ſo
that ſome of them are cut off immediately by the hand of God; and others are
put to death by the hand of Man.</p>
                     <p>As for thoſe Children who live not to a great Age, tho'
they are very du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and obedient to their Parents; God doth make up what is
wanting in the number of their Years here, with an everlaſting Life, and
Glory in Heaven. In which caſe there's no cauſe to complain, as if Cod did
not fulfil his promiſe to them. For as there is no reaſon for a Man to
complain, who is employed to work for ſo much a day, if his Maſter ſee it
fit to free him from his Work, and pay him all his Wages before the third part
of his time is out: Even ſo, if God think fit to ſet his Children at
Liberty, from the toil and labour of this life, and to beſtow upon them
Glorious and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Rewards, while they are in the Morning or Noon, as it
were, of their Age, there is no ground of complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his doing ſo, but
rather great matter of Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto <pb n="51" facs="tcp:94705:28"/>
him, whoſe Mercy and Love is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great.</p>
                     <p>But beſides this Reward in the other World; there are
Temporal Bleſſings which God will beſtow on thoſe who keep this
Commandment. <hi>My Son,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 1.8,9. <hi>Hear
the Inſtruction of thy Father, and forſake not the Law of thy Mother. For
they ſhall be an Ornament of Grace unto thy Head, and Chains about thy
Neck.</hi> That is, if thou art obedient to the Commands of thy Parents, this
will make thee very amiable not only in the ſight of God, but even of Men,
who cannot but love and eſteem ſuch Children, who carry themſelves as
they ought to do towards their Parents.</p>
                     <p>But further, to encourage Children to honour their Parents,
there is a promiſe of Proſperity added to that of long life, <hi>Deut.</hi>
5.16. <hi>That thy days may be prolonged, and that it may go well with
thee,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame Promiſe is repeated, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.3. with
this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence only, that it is prefixed to the promiſe of long life,
<hi>that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayeſt live long on the
Earth.</hi> When God does pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Years of his Children, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten 
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94705:29"/> affords them more or leſs of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Proſperity
alſo, as he ſees it will turn to their good, that ſo their long life may
be the more ſweet and comfortable to them.</p>
                     <p>How acceptable and pleaſing to God was the Obedience of
the <hi>Rechabites</hi> unto their Father, tho' his Commands ſeemed very hard
and ſevere, to wit, <hi>That they ſhould drink no Wine, nor build Houſe,
nor ſow Seed, nor plant Vineyard, nor have any, but ſhould dwell in
Tents,</hi> Jer. 35.6,7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ver. 18. Jeremiah <hi>ſaid
unto the Houſe of the</hi> Rechabites, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,
the God of Iſrael, becauſe you have obeyed the Command of</hi> Jonadab
<hi>your Father, and kept all his Precepts, and done according to all that he
hath Commanded you: Therefore thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, the God of
Iſrael,</hi> Jonadab <hi>the Son of</hi> Rechab <hi>ſhall not want a Man to
ſtand before me for ever.</hi> Which words import, that he would take a
particular care of them, that he would be mindful of them, and have them in his
Eye; that he would preſerve them, and ſhew them his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and love, and
continue unto them thoſe Offices and Priviledges which <pb n="53" facs="tcp:94705:29"/>
they enjoyed, which ſome think were, of being Scribes and Doctors of the Law,
and having ſome Charge in or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Temple.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">3. Motive, from the Example of our
Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</note>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Beſides the Command of God, and
the Reward which he hath promiſed to them who honour their Parents, how
ſtrong an Argument ought it to be unto all Children, to excite them to this,
when they conſider the Example of their Bleſſed Lord and Maſter, their
King and Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt? of whom it is ſaid, <hi>that he was
ſubject unto his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Luke</hi> 2.51. And if he, who was ſo much
greater than his Parents, who was their Lord, their King, their Maker, their
Saviour, and Redeemer; if he, who was the Son of God, and <hi>thought it no
Robbery to be equal with God,</hi> I ſay, if he was ſubject to his Parents,
ought not all Children to be ſo to their Parents? and to eſteem it their
Glory to imitate their Prince and Saviour, as in his other Virtues, ſo in his
Obedience and Subjection to his Parents? Shall any Man think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too
good to do this, when Chriſt did it before him? Can it be too mean 
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94705:30"/> for a Worm to do that, which a Man, a great Man, and a
mighty Prince hath done? Shall vile Sinners think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves abaſed and
diſhonoured by doing that which was done before by him, <hi>who knew no
ſin, and in whoſe Mouth there was found no guile,</hi> who was <hi>holy,
harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and undefiled, ſeparate from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and made higher than
the Heavens, Heb.</hi> 7.26.</p>
                     <p>As our Bleſſed Lord was a great and Noble Pattern to us
in other things, ſo particularly in his love to his Parents. When he was upon
the Croſs, a little before he gave up the Ghoſt, he expreſſed how great
his love was to his Mother, and how tender a care he had of her. John 19.25,26,27. <hi>Now there ſtood by the Croſs of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, his Mother, and his
Mother's Siſter,</hi> Mary <hi>the Wife of</hi> Cleophas, <hi>and</hi> Mary
Magdalene. <hi>When Jeſus therefore ſaw his Mother, and the Diſciple
ſtanding by whom he loved, he ſaith unto his Mother, Woman, behold thy Son.
Then ſaith he to the Diſciple, behold thy Mother. And from that hour, that
Diſciple took her unto his own home.</hi> He commends his Mother to
<hi>John</hi> (<hi>Joſeph</hi> in all probability being dead) that he might
take care of her, <pb n="55" facs="tcp:94705:30"/> as of his own Mother. Tho' he was at
this time in the midſt of great pain and anguiſh, tho' his hands and his
feet were nailed to the Croſs, tho' his Head was Crowned with Thorns, tho' he
lay under the moſt inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Burden that ever Man lay under, yet, as
if the ſight of his Mother had made him forget all his Sufferings and
Torments, he affectionately recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends her to the care of another, who he knew
would perform all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a loving Son unto her. He knew how great an
affliction it would be to her, to be deprived of the Comfort of his preſence
in the World; he knew to how many neceſſities and wants, ſhe ſhould be
expoſed by his leaving of her; and therefore he gives it in charge to the
beloved Diſciple, to do the Duty of a Son unto her, to be to her in his
ſtead, to honour her, to love her, to ſerve her, to take care of her, and
provide whatever might be fit for her. This ſhews all Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren what is their
Duty towards their Parents, to wit, that they ought to take care of them, ſo
long as they live, and are able to do it; they ought with all reſpect and
kindneſs, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form <pb n="56" facs="tcp:94705:31"/> unto them all thoſe Offices,
which the Laws of Nature and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity require.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">4. Motive, from the Examples of ſome
Heathens.</note>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> May not the Examples of ſome Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,
which have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been mentioned, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Chriſtian Children to perform
their Duty to their Parents? There are a great many more Inſtances might be
added to this purpoſe; I ſhall only mention a few. The <hi>firſt</hi> is,

<note n="*" place="margin">Valer. Max. l. 5. c. 4. &amp; Plut.
in Coriola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>of the brave
<hi>Corio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus,</hi> that Great <hi>Roman</hi> Commander, who being very ill
uſed by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, fled to the <hi>Volſcians,</hi> who were at that
time at War with the <hi>Romans.</hi> Within a little time after his coming
amongſt them, he was made General of their Forces; in which Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he had
great Succeſs againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> gaining ſeveral Victories over
them, whereby he was encouraged to approach to the very Walls of <hi>Rome:</hi>
His Countrey-men were terribly alarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this; ſo that they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
to make humble Addreſſes to him, to deprecate his diſpleaſure, but to
no purpoſe: They ſent their Prieſts in <pb n="57" facs="tcp:94705:31"/> their Sacred
Veſtments, but to as little Effect: But no ſooner did his Mother, attended
with his Wife and Children, come to him, but he ſubmitted himſelf to her. 
<q rend="inline">"Now, ſays he, you have overcome me
indeed, when the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties of my Mother are added to yours; tho'
<hi>Rome</hi> deſerve my hatred, yet for my Mother's ſake I will ſpare
it;"</q> and immediately he withdrew his Army.</p>
                     <p>A <hi>ſecond</hi> Example, is that of the Worthy
<hi>Athenian</hi> Captain <hi>Cimon,</hi> 
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Val. Max. ibid.</note>who not being
able to redeem the Corps of his Father, which was Arreſted for Debt, ſold
himſelf, and became a Slave, that his Deceaſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Body might be
freed from that Arreſt that was upon it, and ſo might have Honourable
Burial. This great Man was famous for his Noble and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Exploits, for his
great Courage and Excellent Conduct in Military Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; but there was not any
thing for which he was ſo much admired and loved, as for this wonderful
inſtance of Affection and Reſpect to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:94705:32"/>A Third Example, is, 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Sen.</hi> l. 1.
<hi>Controverſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> c. 1.</note>of a Son, whoſe Father and Uncle
were at great variance. It happ'ned that the Uncle, during this Contention,
fell into great want. His Brother was ſo madly and wickedly ſet againſt
him, that he not only would not relieve him himſelf, but alſo forbad his
Son to do it. The young Man conſidered his Uncles Caſe to be ſuch, as
obliged his Father and himſelf both, to help him all they could: But if his
Father, through his violent Paſſion and Prejudice neglected his Duty, which
the Laws of Nature and Humanity required, yet he judged himſelf bound to do
him all the Service he could, and not to ſuffer him to ſtarve for want,
when it was in his power to ſupport him. The Father being inraged againſt
his Son, becauſe he took pity upon his Uncle, diſinherited him; which the
young Man bore very patiently. His Uncle ſeeing how unjuſtly he was dealt
with, adopted him, and made him his Heir. After ſome time the Uncle grew very
Rich, having got a good Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; but the Father grew poor, and was not
able to maintain himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <pb n="59" facs="tcp:94705:32"/> relief from others.
The Uncle continuing ſtill in his bitter Enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Brother,
forbad the young Man to help him: But ſuch was his Love and Dutifulneſs to
his Father, that notwithſtanding his former Injuſtice and ſeverity
againſt him, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Commands of his Uncle, he took care
of him, and did not ſuffer him to want for any thing, that he was able to
afford him. The Uncle was ſo provoked, by his Adopted Sons kindneſs to his
Natural Parent; that he likewiſe diſinherited him. But the pious Son,
continued to do what he thought his Duty, amidſt all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements
he met with.</p>
                     <p>May not ſuch ſhining Patterns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Pagans,
make many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians aſhamed, who come ſo far ſhort of them, in their
Duty and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Parents? Shall not they riſe up in Judgment and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Chriſtians? who, tho' they have a more excellent, compleat, and
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Rule, tho' they have a great deal more Light to direct them in their
Duty to their Parents; and tho' they have much greater aſſiſtances to
enable them to perform their Duty; do never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs <pb n="60" facs="tcp:94705:33"/>
carry themſelves ſo undutifully, and unchriſtianly, as if they had never
heard of the Goſpel of Chriſt, yea, as if they had been born without any
impreſſions of Natural Religion on their Minds, whereby all Nations are
ſo far inſtructed and enlightned, as to acknowledge, that to honour, obey,
love, ſerve, and aſſiſt our Parents, are Duties of unqueſtionable and
indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Obligation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>The Concluſion, ſhewing how Children ought to improve
what hath been ſaid.</head>
                     <p>From what hath been ſaid, Children may ſee how great
reaſon they have to perform all thoſe Offices of Love, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and
Subjection to their Parents, that God requires of them. It remains that they
ſeriouſly and impartially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what their practice has been, and
whether they have done thoſe things which God requires them to do to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
their Father and Mother.</p>
                     <p>That you may do this to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it's fit that you
employ ſome time in looking back on your Lives, in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how you
have honoured, loved, and obeyed your Parents; that you may <pb n="61" facs="tcp:94705:33"/> ſee, whether you have carried your ſelves towards them, in words
and deeds, as became good Children, who have a ſenſe of Religion; or
whether you have not diſhonoured, neglected, and diſobeyed them.</p>
                     <p>If upon Examination of your ſelves, you find that you have
done your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that you have ſincerely endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to obey them in all
things; that you have loved them heartily, and payed them that Reſpect which
you knew was due unto them: Bleſs God, who hath <hi>given you to will and to
do according to his good Pleaſure.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are defects and
imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which cleave to our exacteſt performances, therefore it is
needful that you beg of God to forgive you, wherein ſoever, through
Ignorance, you have been faulty or defective in thoſe Duties you owed
them.</p>
                     <p>But if upon inquiry into your Hearts and Lives, you find
that you have wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully neglected to do what you ought to have done; if
inſtead of honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, you have diſhonoured them, you have ſlighted
and deſpiſed them, you have mocked and ſcorned them, you have reviled and
reproached them; <pb n="62" facs="tcp:94705:34"/> if inſtead of obeying them, you find
that you have been ſtubborn and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to them, you have refuſed to
follow their Counſels and Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you have done your own Will, and
followed your own vain humour and fancy, in contempt of their Will; if
inſtead of ſubmitting to their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and Chaſtenings, you have
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſubmiſſion to them, and perhaps have rebelled againſt them;
if inſtead of loving them, you have hated them, and wiſhed, and deſired
their Death; if inſtead of relieving them in their wants, and ſupplying
them with what was neceſſary for them, you have waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their
ſubſtance by your riotous and extravagant Living, you have put off all
bowels of compaſſion and tenderneſs towards them; if, I ſay, you find
that you have thus carried your ſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, in a way ſo contrary
to your Duty, how ought you to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mourn for your wickedneſs and
folly? How ought you to accuſe your ſelves for your great iniquity, and to
aggravate your Crimes by all juſt and fit conſiderations?</p>
                     <p>You may in this manner expoſtulate the caſe with your
ſelves: <hi>What a ſad <pb n="63" facs="tcp:94705:34"/> and unworthy Wretch am I, who
have thus diſhonoured, hated, and diſobeyed my dear Parents, who are under
God the Authors of my Being in the World, to whom I owe that I am! who have
proved ſo undutiful to them who took care of me, when I could not take care
of my ſelf; who fed and cloathed me, who were at ſo great pains and charge
for me, who have employed ſo much of their time and ſtrength to provide for
me all neceſſary things; and yet that I ſhould prove ſo wicked as to
deſpiſe them, to diſobey them, and hate them, not to ſubmit my ſelf
unto them, what baſe and wicked ingratitude is it! That I, who ſhould have
been a Bleſſing to them, ſhould prove a Curſe! That I who ſhould have
been a Comfort to them, ſhould he the cauſe of their grief and ſorrow!
That I who ſhould have been a help unto them, ſhould be ſo great a
hinderance! That I who ſhould have been the ſtay and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of their
Old Age, ſhould prove their ruine, and the cauſe of the ſpending of their
days in anguiſh and trouble! What a prodigious impiety is this! What a
wretched and abominable Creature am I, who have been guilty of ſuch horrid
wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs! Who have had ſo little regard <pb n="64" facs="tcp:94705:35"/> to thoſe
who are to me in God's ſtead here in the World! What puniſhment do I not
deſerve! What a wonder is it that God hath ſpared me and pitied me, and
hath not cut me off in the midſt of my diſobedience, neglect, and contempt
of my dear Parents! That he hath not made me an Example to all others, and a
ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Monument of his juſt diſpleaſure! That he has not bound me
hand and foot, and caſt me into utter darkneſs, and given me my portion
with Hypocrites and Sinners; but hath lengthened out my years, and given me
time and place to repent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Having thus in your own minds ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulated the matter
with your ſelves, you may in the next place adore and bleſs the Divine
Goodneſs, the infinite Mercy, and aſtoniſhing Kindneſs of God towards
you, in having ſpared and pitied you; in not dealing with you after your
ſins, nor rewarding you after your iniquities; but that he hath been
pleaſed to wait to be gracious to you. Humbly confeſs your faults and
offences unto him; with great ſhame and confuſion of face, and with true
grief and ſorrow of heart ackowledge <pb n="65" facs="tcp:94705:35"/> your iniquities;
make particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ſo far as you remember, of your
ſtubbornneſs and diſobedience to your Parents, of your contempt and
neglect of them, of your hating them, and wiſhing Evil to them, of your
ſpeaking irreverently and wickedly to them, or of them, of your not
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to their Corrections, of your not heeding their Admonitions and
Counſels, nor regarding their juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beg of God,
for Chriſt's ſake, to have mercy on you, and to blot out your Sins, and to
make you what you ought to be.</p>
                     <p>After this, it is fit to form ſincere and hearty
Reſolutions of doing your Duty, in all reſpects, to your Parents, for the
time to come; of loving, honouring, obeying, and ſerving them, as you ought
to do. Reſolve to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend whatever has been amiſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective either in
your thoughts, words, or deeds, with relation to them. Beg of God, to
ſtrengthen you in your Reſolutions; to fortifie you againſt all
Temptations; to inſpire you with his Fear and Love; to guide you by his good
Spirit; and that he would never leave you, nor forſake you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:94705:36"/>If the Example and Society of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
wicked Children has been an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of making you ſo bad, and of
hardening you in your Contempt, Stubbornneſs, and Diſobedience; reſolve
to break off your Familiarities with them; let them and all others know, and
ſee, that you are ſorry for your Diſobedience to your Parents; for your
having diſhonoured, ſlighted, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected them; and that you are
reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to do ſo no more; but will, by the help of God, approve your
ſelves Dutiful, Kind, and Obedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                     <p>Not only muſt you in this manner make your Humble and
Penitent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to Almighty God, your Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, whom you have
provoked, as by your other Sins, ſo particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by your diſobedience to
your Parents, and by your diſhonouring of them; but you muſt likewiſe
confeſs unto your Parents the Crimes whereof you have been guilty againſt
them; you muſt ſay as the Prodigal did, <hi>I will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and go to my
Father, and will ſay unto him, Father, I have ſinned againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and
before thee; and am no more <pb n="67" facs="tcp:94705:36"/> worthy to be called thy
Son,</hi> Luke 15.18,19. Let your Parents ſee that you are heartily ſorry
for your Offences againſt them by Word or Deed; beg of them to forgive you,
and deſire them to pray to God that he would forgive you.</p>
                     <p>You are to be careful after this, to fulfil your Purpoſes
and Reſolutions, and to perform all thoſe Duties of Love, Honour, and
Obedience to your Parents, wherein you were formerly ſo defective. For this
end it is fit, daily and earneſtly to beg of God, that he would direct and
aſſiſt you by his Holy Spirit, to do what is well-pleaſing in his
ſight. It is neceſſary for you to be very jealous of your deceitful and
deſperately wicked Hearts; to watch over them carefully, leſt they turn
aſide towards your former crooked Ways; leſt you return <hi>with the Dog to
the Vomit.</hi> Watch againſt all thoſe Temptations, whereby you are moſt
in danger of being ſeduced, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled again in your former perverſe
Practices and Cuſtoms.</p>
                     <p>As you have been formerly very neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and defective in
Honouring and <pb n="68" facs="tcp:94705:37"/> Obeying your Parents, endeavour for the
future ſo much the more, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all thoſe Duties which you owe unto
them, with great care and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs.</p>
                     <p>As you have been great Examples of Diſobedience, ſtrive
to be ſo much the greater Patterns of Obedience. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to do all that
you can, that they who have been, by your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels or Examples, corrupted,
and made ſtubborn, and diſobedient, may be reformed, and reſcued from
their Sins and Wickedneſs; that as you have been Inſtruments to promote
Satan's Kingdom, ſo you may be zealous for the glory of God, for promoting
Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and true Virtue in the World, whereof this is no inconſiderable part,
that <hi>Children Honour their Father and Mother, and do all thoſe Duties
with chearfulneſs unto them, which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is the way to obtain the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine pardon, to turn away
his Wrath, and to keep off thoſe heavy Judgments which are threatned
againſt ſtubborn Children, and ſuch who mock and ſcorn their Parents:
Or if God ſee it <pb n="69" facs="tcp:94705:37"/> fit to puniſh you here, he will make
your Corrections and Puniſhments, and all other things, <hi>work together for
your good;</hi> and after he hath tryed you, he will beſtow upon you rewards
of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life and Glory.</p>
                     <p>As for thoſe who are ſo perverſe as to deſpiſe all
Counſel and Advice, who refuſe to hearken to any Inſtructions, who are
reſolved to go on in their ſtubbornneſs and diſobedience to their
Parents, in ſlighting and vilifying them; let them remember what the Wiſe
Man ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Rejoice, O young Man, in thy Youth,
and let thine heart chear thee, in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways
of thine heart, and in the ſight of thine Eyes: But know thou, that for all
theſe things, God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="appendix">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:94705:38"/>
                  <head>An Appendix concerning the Duties of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their
Step-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Duties of Children to their
Step-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note>HAving ſpoken of the Duties of Children to their Natural
Parents, I ſhall add a few things concerning their Duties to their
Step-Parents.</p>
                     <p>Children ought to honour their Step-Parents, to carry
themſelves Reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully towards them, and to avoid eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, either in
words or deeds, which has an appearance of Neglect and Contempt.</p>
                     <p>They ought to Obey them, and to ſhew great readineſs to
ſerve them, in any thing that is in their power to do for them; and to avoid
whatever looks like ſtubbornneſs, eſpecially in ſuch things, wherein
their Natural Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent requires them to be Obedient to their Step-Parent.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:94705:38"/>They ought to carry themſelves kindly
and lovingly towards them, and to avoid whatever looks like Hatred or
Malice.</p>
                     <p>They ought to ſubmit to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, and to their
Chaſtenings, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when their Natural Parent deſires the
Step-Parent to reprove or correct them for their faults.</p>
                     <p>They ought to hearken to their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, to follow their
good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Examples, and to be thankful for whatever they either do
or ſay for their benefit and advantage.</p>
                     <p>They ought to bear patiently with my thing, in their humour
and temper, that is not ſo ſweet and pleaſant; and to beware, leſt they
be thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, to do or ſay what becometh not Children, towards
thoſe who are in the place of Parents to them.</p>
                     <p>As to theſe particular Duties, I thought it needleſs to
ſay much, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving treated of them more fully in the preceeding Diſcourſe,
about Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Duties to their Natural Parents: I ſhall therefore in the
next place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:94705:39"/>
                     <head>Some Motives to ſtir up Children to be Dutiful to their
Step-Parents.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Some Motives to ſtir up Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be
Duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to them.</note>The <hi>firſt</hi> thing which ſhould prevail with
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to carry themſelves Dutifully towards their Step-Parents, is the
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that is due to the Laws of God, whereby it is declared that Man and
Wife <hi>are no more twain, but one Fleſh;</hi> They are, by Marriage, united
in the neareſt and cloſeſt manner that can be. From whence it follows, by
a very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Conſequence, that 'tis the Duty of Children to carry
themſelves in the moſt reſpectful and loving manner, that is
poſſible, towards thoſe who are, by Marriage, made one with their Natural
Parents.</p>
                     <p n="2">2dly. The Reſpect and Love that Children owe to
their Natural Parents, oblige them to ſhew the utmoſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and all
ſincere Affection, to thoſe whom they have taken into ſo near a Relation
with themſelves. We ſee what the Laws of Friendſhip do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men,
who are very careful to ſhew all poſſible Reſpect and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs 
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94705:39"/> to thoſe, for whom their Friends have a great Value and
Affection. How much more ought Children to love, honour, and ſerve thoſe
whom their Parents have made one with themſelves, by chuſing them into ſo
near and cloſe a Relation and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
                     <p n="3">3dly. Does not even Prudence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to all this?
Is not this the way to ingage their Step-Parents to be reſpectful, kind, and
ſerviceable to them, and ready to do them all good Offices? Tho' there are
ſome Step-Parents of ſo barbarous and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage a Temper, that nothing can
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them, or work upon them; yet there are but few, in compariſon, who
will not be affected and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon with Kindneſs, Reſpect, and good
Offices, eſpecially when they are not for a ſhort time, but of long
continuance.</p>
                     <p n="4">4thly. Does not Self-Love likewiſe oblige Children
to do theſe things? This is the way for them to make their lives eaſie and
comfortable, to enjoy a great deal of Peace, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of Mind: When
they reflect upon their having done what is ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <pb n="74" facs="tcp:94705:40"/> to
the Laws of Religion, to the Rules which the Wiſdom from above layeth down,
it muſt needs afford them a very ſenſible Pleaſure and great
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; whereas, by carrying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves undutifully, they bring upon
themſelves a great deal of Vexation and Trouble; they not only alienate more
and more the Affection of their Step-Parents, but they likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke
their Natural Parents to be leſs kind to them, if not quite to turn their
Backs upon them.</p>
                     <p>From what hath been ſaid, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears how great reaſon
Children have to carry themſelves with great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Love, and with
all poſſible Dutifulneſs towards their Step-Parents. 
<note place="margin">Againſt thoſe who are undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful
towards their Step-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note>How greatly therefore are they to be blamed,
who make no Conſcience of doing their Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them? There are many who
make it their buſineſs to vex and torment their Step-Parents, to affront
them, and to diſgrace them: They are very ready to aggravate all their
Weakneſſes and Imperfections, and do thereby endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to cauſe others
to hate and to <pb n="75" facs="tcp:94705:40"/> deſpiſe them; they invent too often a
great many things which they charge them with, that ſo they may by any means,
tho' never ſo wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, render them odious and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. And,
which is worſt of all, they do all that ever they can, by the moſt impious
arts that malicious and Deviliſh Wit can contrive, to alienate from them the
affections of their Natural Parents, and to ſet them together by the ears; by
which means very dreadful and Tragical Effects do oft-times follow, when
Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Wife are inflamed one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another. <hi>Where Envying and
Strife is,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>there
is Confuſion and every evil Work.</hi> How often do ſuch Diſcords and
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions end in the utter Ruin and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction both of Parents and
Children? <hi>Every Houſe divided againſt it ſelf,</hi> ſaith our
Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.25. <hi>ſhall not ſtand.</hi> And therefore, let
all thoſe who have any regard to the Honour of God, who have any thing of
ſincere Affection to their Natural Parents, who deſire to live in Peace,
who wiſh well to the Families to which they belong, and are willing to
prevent their utter Ruin <pb n="76" facs="tcp:94705:41"/> and Deſolation, let all ſuch,
I ſay, as have any ſenſe of theſe things, be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to behave
themſelves with all due Reſpect and Love towards thoſe who are in the
place of Parents to them. By doing whereof, as they will gain the Love and
Reſpect of all who are wiſe and good, ſo they may be aſſured of
obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God great and laſting Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which he never fails to
beſtow on all thoſe who ſincerely endeavour to Obey his Laws, and who
ſeek his Glory.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:94705:41"/>
                  <p>A DISCOURSE About the RIGHT WAY Of Improving our TIME.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>James Kirkwood,</hi> Rector of <hi>Aſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> in
<hi>Bedfordſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Second Edition Corrected and Enlarged.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Tayler</hi> at the Ship
in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, and <hi>John E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veringham</hi> at the Star
in <hi>Ludgate-Street,</hi> near the Weſt-End of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
1693.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:94705:42"/>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:94705:42"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Epheſ. V. 16.</bibl> 
                        <p>Redeeming the time, becauſe the days are evil.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="introduction">
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note>OF all the
outward Bleſſings, which God beſtows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, there is none ſo
valuable and precious as our Time. God beſtows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us his other
Bleſſings in great variety and plenty; but in this he ſeems to be more
ſparing, for it is given us not in large proportions, but as it were drop by
drop, one minute after another; never two minutes together: when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he gives
us one, he takes away another. And yet how ſtrange is it to think, that a
great many ſpend their time in Vanity and Folly! Time is to many like a dead
Commodity; they cannot tell what to do with it; they are ready to throw it away
for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <pb n="80" facs="tcp:94705:43"/> or for that which is little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:
inſtead of improving and uſing it in virtuous and profitable actions and
deſigns, they waſte it in trifling and vanity, which is an Argument of the
greateſt Folly; as on the other hand, the right husbanding of Time, is a
great Inſtance of true Wiſdom.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</note>The Apoſtle
having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to <hi>walk circumſpectly, not as
fools, but as wiſe,</hi> he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſubjoins <hi>[Redeeming the
time.]</hi> Intimating thereby, that there is no better way for us to ſhew
our ſelves wiſe, than by employing our time to good purpoſe, Redeeming
and buying it; or, as ſome read the words, <hi>Buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Opportunity,</hi>
or a fit occaſion and ſeaſon for doing good. It is a Metaphor taken from
Merchants, who, when they have a great likelyhood and probability, of making
conſiderable gain and advantage in buying and ſelling, part with their
pleaſures, or leſſer cares and concerns, that they may make a good
bargain, and purchaſe that which they greatly deſire. So the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
the Man that is good and wiſe, ought to deny himſelf in his Pleaſures 
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94705:43"/> and outward delights, or even in his ordinary affairs and
concerns, when he has any great proſpect of doing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what conſiderable,
for the glory of God, the good of his Neighbour, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his own
Soul.</p>
                     <p>The reaſon which the Apoſtle uſeth, is, <hi>[Becauſe
the days are evil]</hi> that is, either bad and ſinful, full of wickedneſs
and folly; ſo that it is very hard and difficult then to be good, when ſin,
like a violent and impetuous Torrent, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries all down before it: This ought
to make you redeem all occaſions of doing good, that you may fortifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
in Virtue and Piety, that you may reſcue thoſe that are carried down the
ſtream by bad Example, and may build up your ſelves in Holineſs, and that
you may be made <hi>ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might.</hi>
Or <hi>[Becauſe the days are evil]</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the danger you are in
through the fury and malice of your Enemies, who are ready to do you all the
miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that is in their power; the ſenſe whereof ſhould make you
improve all occaſions of doing good, not knowing how ſoon you may be
deprived of your <pb n="82" facs="tcp:94705:44"/> preſent happy opportunities and
ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for working.</p>
                     <p>The deſign of this Diſcourſe, is, to ſhew you;
1ſt, How you are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem your Time: And, 2dly, To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome
Conſiderations to excite you to do ſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>How Time is to be redeemed.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. Time to be redeemed from
ſleep.</note>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> YOu are to redeem your Time from exceſſive
and immoderate ſleep. It is neceſſary for all Men to refreſh their
Bodies with ſleep and reſt; and the ſtate of ſome Mens Bodies requires
a great deal more than others; ſo that no exact Rules can be given about the
propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſleep that's proper for every one: Only in general, it is fit
that all Perſons redeem as much time from ſleeping, as the health of their
Bodies can permit; that ſo they may employ part of that time to ſome good
and uſeful purpoſe, which they were wont to waſte in the ſhadow of
Death, as it were; whereof ſleep is the picture and repreſentation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:94705:44"/>In the ancient Church we find, many were
wont to riſe up in the night to pray, that ſo they might day and night keep
alive in their Souls Divine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; that they might preſerve a
reliſh and taſte of heavenly and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things; that excellent
Objects might not be removed too far out of their ſight. This is a practice,
which, perhaps, very few in theſe cold Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are able ſafely to
imitate; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at ſome times of the year. The weakneſs and
tenderneſs of ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies makes it to them impracticable; becauſe it
would render them unfit at other times, not only for religious performances,
but for the other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Actions of life. Some likewiſe have ſo
little time allowed them for their repoſe in the Night, that they cannot do
this, in their preſent Circumſtances. As for ſuch who are capable,
without any ſort of inconvenience, to follow this ancient Practice, let them
do it: They want not ſufficient Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereto, if they conſider
that thereby they have the opportunity of flying, as it were, from theſe
Regions of darkneſs and miſery, of ſin and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, unto thoſe glorious
Regions of light <pb n="84" facs="tcp:94705:45"/> and happineſs, of purity and
perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; there to converſe with God their chiefeſt Joy; to behold his
Face, the light of his Countenance; to taſte and ſee how good he is; to
walk with him; to be ſatisfied with his Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to drink of thoſe
Rivers of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed pleaſure, which are in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>the ſtreams
whereof make glad the City of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As for thoſe, who are not able to deny themſelves of
their repoſe in the night ſeaſon; all that I ſhall ſay to them, is
this; When at ſome times it pleaſeth God to take away their ſleep, and to
keep them awake, let them redeem a few moments from vain thoughts, by lifting
up their Souls to God, darting up ſome pious thoughts and fervent deſires
Heaven-wards; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on the Goodneſs and Love of God; admiring his
glorious Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; calling to mind, and conſidering his gracious
Providences; longing for, and breathing after that happy State when they
ſhall be placed above all the infirmities and frailties of the fleſh, above
outward neceſſities, above Sin and Satan, and all their Enemies: And after
this, they may again compoſe <pb n="85" facs="tcp:94705:45"/> themſelves to ſleep.
This is a means to keep the Soul awake, to entertain it in a way worthy of it,
to accuſtom it to the contemplation of excellent and divine Objects, to keep
Heaven always near its view; and not to ſuffer the things of another life, to
be removed too far out of ſight. We ſee in what temper of mind the Spouſe
was, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. <hi>I ſleep, but my heart waketh.</hi> Even amidſt
her repoſe and ſleep, her thoughts were running after her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable and
beloved Object, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed her heart, and filled her thoughts
when ſhe was awake. And ſo it is with pious Souls ſometimes, when their
thoughts have been much imployed and buſied about ſpiritual and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
things in the day time, they dream of them in the Night ſeaſon. <hi>Tho'
they ſleep, yet their heart waketh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This watchful temper is an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent means to enrich the
Soul; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſlothfulneſs, and giving up ones ſelf to drowſineſs
and ſleep, cauſeth ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual beggery. <hi>An idle Soul</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 19.15.) <hi>ſhall ſuffer hunger.</hi> And,
<hi>Prov.</hi> 20.13. <hi>Love not ſleep, teſt thou come to Poverty: Open
thine Eyes, and thou ſhalt be ſatisfied with Bread.</hi> Then 
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:94705:46"/> was it that <hi>Samſon</hi> loſt his Hair, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
was his ſtrength, when he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep. <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.19.</p>
                     <p>As it is a fault at any time to waſte our precious hours
in this ſluggiſh and lazy manner, ſo eſpecially when God affords very
favourable opportunities of doing ſome great good to our ſelves or others.
<hi>He that ſleepeth in Harveſt</hi> (ſaith the wiſe Man,) <hi>is a Son
that cauſeth ſhame; Prov.</hi> 10.5. that is, he makes his Father and
Friends aſhamed of him, and brings ſhame and diſgrace on himſelf.</p>
                     <p>Now is the day of Grace, now is the acceptable time, now is
the ſeaſon of gathering the Fruits of Righteouſneſs, and of making
ſure an Harveſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Glory. <hi>And therefore, let us not
ſleep, as do others; but let us watch and be ſober,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
5.6.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2. Time to be redeemed from dreſſing
the Body.</note>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Redeem time from dreſſing and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Body: Let not more time be ſpent that way than is meet and fit. Let your
firſt care every day be to dreſs and adorn the better part, to put on the
true Ornaments, to cloath your ſelves with Humility, Meekneſs, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:94705:46"/> Charity, and with all other Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which are of great
price in the ſight of God. <hi>Put off the Works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and put on
the Armour of Light.</hi> Raiſe your Souls towards Heaven, by ſome ſhort
and fervent Ejaculations. Read the Word of God with great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and
humility, with an earneſt deſire to know his Will, and with a ſincere
purpoſe to do it. Endeavour to feed and nouriſh your Souls by ſerious
Meditation. Call on God, by humble and earneſt Prayer, to pardon you, to
bleſs you, to direct and proſper you in all your ways, and to ſave and
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you from all Evils, Ghoſtly and Bodily. Form good purpoſes and
ſtrong reſolutions, to do what is good and right. Set the Lord always
before you. Reſolve to ſeek his Glory in all things, whether you eat or
drink, or whatever elſe you do.</p>
                     <p>After having done thoſe things which are needful for the
Soul, you may next do what is fit and decent as to your Attire and Cloathing,
according to your Circumſtances in the World. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware leſt you pride your
ſelves in your Apparel: Do not therein gratifie your Vanity, to go beyond
others of your <pb n="88" facs="tcp:94705:47"/> Rank and Quality, to make your ſelves be
taken notice of more than others. Too great care about adorning the outward
Man, gives juſt cauſe to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that the chief buſineſs is
neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
                     <p>Conſider what it is that you deck and adorn with ſo much
care and coſt; even a poor, vile, ſinful Body, that's full of rottenneſs
and corruption; conſider that within a little while it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a very
ugly, deformed, and ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Carcaſs, and be food to the Worms.</p>
                     <p>If they who beſtow ſo much time every day in painting
and patching, and ſuch like things, would but beſtow a few Minutes in
thinking of the Grave, and what the Body will become with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a very little
time, ſo vile and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, that even they who do love it moſt dearly,
will then avoid it, and be glad to have it removed out of their ſight; and
that their face, which now they themſelves admire ſo much, and which they
are ready to think every body elſe admires likewiſe, ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a
ſhort time be eaten thorough by vile Worms, and waſted and made ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with
Rottenneſs and Corruption, and that all its Beauty ſhall be marred: I 
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:94705:47"/> ſay, if vain Perſons would ſometimes think of
theſe things, and behold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves now and then in this Glaſs, how
would it humble them, and make them leſs addicted to ſuch vain Imployment,
and be more buſied in things of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conſequence! This would turn
their thoughts another way, and make them beſtow a little more pains to
waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Impurities of their Souls. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is written
againſt thoſe who are guilty of this vanity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance in Apparel
and Ornaments. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.16. and 17. <hi>Moreover the Lord faith,
becauſe the Daughters of</hi> Sion <hi>are haughty, and walk with ſtretched
forth Necks and wanton Eyes, walking and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing as they go, and making a
tinkling with their feet; Therefore the Lord will ſmite with a Scab, the
Crown of the Head of the Daughters of</hi> Sion, &amp;c. And verſe 24. <hi>It
ſhall come to paſs, that inſtead of ſweet ſmell, there ſhall be
ſtink; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Girdle, a Rent; and inſtead of well ſet Hair,
Baldneſs; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Stomacher, a girding of Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and Burning
inſtead of Beauty.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:94705:48"/>
                        <note place="margin">3. Time to be
redeemed from eating and drinking.</note>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Redeem time from
eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from pampering the Body: Spend no more of your time that
way than what is fit. Make not your Belly your God; eat and drink that you may
live, that you may be able to perform the neceſſary actions of life; but do
not live ſo as if you had nothing to do, but to eat and drink, <hi>and to
make provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the Luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> Live
ſoberly at all times, and uſe abſtinence and faſting ſometimes. Take
not too great delight in gratifying your Palate and Appetite. God alloweth you
the free and liberal uſe of his good Creatures, for your health and
refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but not to abuſe them to glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony and drunkenneſs, or any
other ſort of exceſs and extravagance. It is fit to uſe all thoſe
periſhing things with great moderation; becauſe,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> They are apt to be a great Snare, and to
lead Men to a great deal of Sin and Folly. The Apoſtle rekons up firſt
<hi>Gluttony and Drunkenneſs,</hi> and then <hi>Chambering and
Wantonneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Intemperance</hi> being as
the Mother of the reſt. It is often the <pb n="91" facs="tcp:94705:48"/> occaſion and
cauſe of them. The Sin of <hi>Sodom</hi> was occaſioned by <hi>their
ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Bread, and abundance of Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Ezek. 16.49.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> This renders the Soul un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active, and
unfit for thoſe excerciſes, which chiefly belong to it to perform. The
Spirits are thereby made dull and ſleepy, and incapable to be attentive and
ſerious. <hi>Watch and be ſober</hi> muſt go together. If we are not
ſober and temperate, we are not fit to Watch. And therefore our Saviour
ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any
time your hearts be overcharged with ſurfeiting and drunkenneſs, and ſo
that day come upon you unawares.</hi> So long as the Soul lodgeth in the Body,
it depends much upon the ſtate and temper of it, ſo that the Body, when it
is clogg'd and oppreſſed with meat, or drowned with drink, is a very unfit
Tool for the Soul to manage; yea thereby the Soul is, as it were, chained up,
and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not freely move and act. So we ſee that Men at ſuch times, when
they are guilty of exceſs and intemperance, are raſh and imprudent in their
Counſels and Reſolutions, whereof they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed afterwards when they
grow ſober.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="92" facs="tcp:94705:49"/>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The uncertainty of
theſe delights of Senſe ſhould diſpoſe us ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to deny our
ſelves, and not to enſlave our ſelves unto them, and come under the
tyranny of a curious and dainty Palate. A change in our outward eſtate will
be the leſs ſurpriſing to us, when in time of plenty we now and then
reſtrain and deny our ſelves in thoſe pleaſures, which we have the
op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to purſue in our eating and drinking.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">4. Time to be redeemed from
Gaming.</note>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Redeem time from Gaming and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations.
Sometimes they are very needful to the Body, for your health, and to render you
more fit for action and buſineſs. But you muſt take care that your
Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements and Recreations be,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> innocent and lawful, and not contrary to
the Rules and Principles of Chriſtianity; that they be not hurtful to your
ſelves or others, nor ſcandalous and offenſive. Let them not be ſuch as
thoſe of wicked Men, of whom <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.23.
to whom <hi>it is a ſport to do miſchief;</hi> and who <hi>make a mock of
ſin;</hi> whoſe delight and divertiſement is, in <pb n="93" facs="tcp:94705:49"/>
ſaying things that are wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, to the hurt and grief of one or
other. The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> called for <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> (when he was
<hi>their Priſoner</hi>) <hi>to make them ſport,</hi> Judg. 16.25. The
<hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians</hi> required a Song and mirth of the poor Captive
<hi>Jews,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Sing us one of the Songs of</hi> Sion,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.3. They made it a ſport to inſult and to triumph over
others in their diſtreſs; they made themſelves merry with the miſeries
of others.</p>
                     <p n="2">2dly, Let your Divertiſements and Recreations be
uſed with moderation: give not your ſelves liberty to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond due
bounds, neither as to time, nor yet as to the proportion of money you play for.
Beware of falling into the Habit of Gaming; when <hi>Plato</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved a
young Man very ſharply for playing at Dice<note n="†" place="margin">Diog. Laert. in Platone.</note>, the young Gameſter anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
him, <hi>Do you reprove me ſo much for ſo ſmall a matter?</hi> But ſaid
<hi>Plato, Cuſtom is no ſmall matter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is unſpeakable hurt and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, that comes from
ſuffering your ſelves to be too far carried away by the fancy and humour of
Gaming, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <pb n="94" facs="tcp:94705:50"/> your Sports and Paſtimes. This
does inſenſibly expoſe you to the danger of Poverty, as <hi>Solomon</hi>
tells us. <hi>He that loveth Pleaſure ſhall be a poor Man, Prov.</hi>
21.17. This renders you unfit for all Sacred and ſerious Performances, the
mind being thereby filled with the images and reflections of what you ſaid
and heard, of what you and others did at your Games: Your hopes and your fears,
your joys and your uneaſineſs, your victories and loſſes, your
ſurpriſes and diſappointments, your little debates and contentions, your
indignation and reſentments, and a great many other things, too common at
Gaming, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract and fill your mind for a great while afterwards, that
when you would be ſerious, and employ your ſelves to better purpoſe, you
cannot bring your minds to that fixedneſs and ſtayedneſs that is
neceſſary; you remain, as it were, drunk with your Paſtimes and
Divertiſements; your thoughts reel to and fro, and cannot ſettle; you have
a great deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning again to your Recreations, that you may gratifie
your fancy, and may gain more profit, or praiſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:94705:50"/>That you may not fall under thoſe
inconveniencies, your beſt way is to keep out of ſuch Company as makes
Gaming their Buſineſs. And if at any time it be fit for you to indulge your
ſelves a little in Gaming, it will not be amiſs that you ſet Bounds to
yourſelves; both as to your time, how long to play; and as to the quantity of
money you intend to play for; that you may not either in one or t'other
reſpect, exceed thoſe limits which Chriſtian Prudence requires. It is
very adviſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble either not at all to play for money (which oft-times
occaſions great ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and quarrellings, or great unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of
thought;) or to play for ſo very little as may be next to nothing, which may
not afterwards occaſion any uneaſie reflections and diſſatisfaction of
mind. And if at any time you be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and find it expedient to play
for a little more than ordinary, (ſtill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Rules of
diſcretion and Chriſtian Prudence) it would not be unfit to make it a
condition in your Game, that the Winner apply what he gains to ſome
charitable uſe, which you may either then expreſly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or you may
reſolve to give the <pb n="96" facs="tcp:94705:51"/> money which ſhall be gained, to
ſome diſcreet and charitable Perſon, who will be ſure to beſtow it to
good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. As this would afford a great pleaſure and joy to thoſe who
reap ſome fruit and benefit by your Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Paſtime; ſo it would
afford your ſelves a greater delight and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, than otherwiſe
you could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect by your Divertiſements. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, this would prevent
covetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and other evil paſſions and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, which
uſually attend thoſe who game only, or chiefly, for profit and
advantage.</p>
                     <p>As for thoſe who are apt in gaming to be tranſported
into violent paſſion, and to break out into indecent heats, it is
neceſſary for ſuch Perſons to give over all ſuch Divertiſements, as
uſe to cauſe this exceſſive fermentation of their Spirits, and which
put them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fret. Or if at any time they think good to play at ſome
Game, they ought to do it in the preſence of thoſe, who by their Authority
are able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from every thing that is indecent and extravagant,
that by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees they may get the Victory over themſelves, and may habituate
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <pb n="97" facs="tcp:94705:51"/> to mildneſs and gentleneſs of Spirit,
and may be preſerved from all the ſad conſequences of unruly
paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">5. Time to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from
Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting.</note>
                        <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Redeem time from Viſiting. Too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
throw away their time in making vain and unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Viſits, employing
themſelves on theſe occaſions in vain and impertinent chat, and
<hi>fooliſh talking and jeſting, which are not convenient;</hi> in making
their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, and paſſing their Cenſures upon the Words and
Actions, the Modes and Cuſtoms of others; in ſlandering and back-biting; in
ſowing vain and falſe Reports; in cauſing Jealouſies and Contentions,
and doing other ſuch like bad Offices.</p>
                     <p>Viſiting is either good or bad, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is
managed. In ſome caſes it is very fit and neceſſary to viſit your
Friends and Neighbours, to keep up thereby a friendly and neighbourly
Correſpondence, to offer your help and ſervice to them when there is need
of it, to ſympathize with them when they are in any ſort of trouble or
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and to aſſiſt them to bear their <pb n="98" facs="tcp:94705:52"/>
burdens, whether of Body, or Mind, or outward Eſtate.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes the Laws of Civility and Diſcretion require,
that you viſit thoſe who have witneſſed great Civility and Reſpect
towards you. Sometimes the good Offices and generous Favours of ſome
Perſons to you, require that you ſhould expreſs your grateful ſenſe
of their kindneſs and genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, by all poſſible inſtances of
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and eſteem, and particularly by viſiting of them now and then,
which is a very eaſie and a ſmall return for thoſe Obligations they have
laid upon you.</p>
                     <p>You muſt beware of viſiting or fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting the company
of thoſe who are very lewd and wicked, by whoſe converſation you are in
great danger of being corrupted, whoſe example is ready to infect you. When
you ſee a Houſe marked for the Plague, you are careful not to go into it,
you keep your ſelves at a good diſtance from it, that you may not run the
hazard of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The Love which you have for life makes you do all you can
to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. Ought you not then to be as careful to keep out of the
company of <pb n="99" facs="tcp:94705:52"/> prophane perſons, whoſe <hi>Throat is an
open Sepulchre,</hi> whoſe <hi>Mouths are full of Blaſphemy and
Curſing,</hi> whoſe Breath is very infectious, whoſe Words and Actions
are full of moſt deadly Poiſon, whereby your Souls are in danger of being
corrupted and deſtroyed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? <hi>Enter not into the path of the
wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, and go not in the way of evil men. Avoid it,
paſs not by it, turn from it, and paſs away,</hi> Prov. 4.14,15. And
<hi>Chap.</hi> 5.8. He adviſeth young men to <hi>remove their way far from
the ſtrange woman, and not to come nigh the door of her Houſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As you ought to avoid all ſorts of Debauched Company, ſo
eſpecially of thoſe who are Mockers of Religion, who ſcoff at all that is
called Sacred, or looks like ſerious. They who <hi>ſit in the Seat of the
Scornful,</hi> are menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. as the
chief of Sinners, the higheſt Rank of them. Such Perſons are Satan's
prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Inſtruments and Miniſters: Their ſcoffs and flouts do
unſpeakable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to Religion. A great many, who have ſtood firm
againſt Arguments and Perſwaſions, have proved too weak to hold out
againſt the Impious Raillery, <pb n="100" facs="tcp:94705:53"/> and Prophane Jeſting of
ſuch, whoſe buſineſs is, to turn the moſt ſerious things of
Religion into Ridicule. You ought to beware of ſuch Wretches, as the very
peſts of Mankind.</p>
                     <p>It is true, ſometimes your neceſſary Affairs, and your
Relation wherein you ſtand to ſome Perſons, may make it your Duty to be
often in the company of thoſe who are very wicked, but then you ought to be,
<hi>Firſt,</hi> poſſeſſed with a great abhorrence of what is evil in
them, and in no manner to approve their ſin and folly. <hi>Have no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
with their unfruitful works of darkneſs, but rather reprove them,</hi> Eph.
5.11. Follow the Pſalmiſt's Example, whoſe <hi>Eyes ran down with Rivers
of Tears, becauſe they kept not God's Law,</hi> Pſal. 119.136. Remember
alſo how <hi>Lot's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soul was vexed with the filthy Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
of the wicked amongſt whom he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.9,10. <hi>Secondly,</hi>
You ought to make uſe of all favourable op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, to endeavour to make
them better, and to reſcue them from their evil ways and doings.</p>
                     <p>If you obſerve theſe things, you are not partakers with
them in their Sins, and therefore God will not lay them <pb n="101" facs="tcp:94705:53"/>
to your charge. But if you entertain unneceſſary Company, and hold a
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Familiarity, with Perſons of a profligate Life, 'tis too certain
a mark that your Religion goes not very deep. You cannot juſtly be
ſuppoſed to have much love to God, if you take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the Society
of his profeſſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. <hi>All Fleſh conſorteth,</hi> ſaith the
Son of <hi>Sirach, according to kind, and a Man will cleave to his like. What
Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip hath the Wolf with the Lamb? ſo the Sinner with the Godly?</hi>
Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticus 13.16,17.</p>
                     <p>If at any time Atheiſtical and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Perſons follow
after you, and thruſt themſelves into your Company, beware of them, and
ſhake off their Society, unleſs you converſe with them with a deſign to
reform them, and to bring them off from their evil Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and have ground
to hope that you may do them good. But when after having tried twice or thrice
to make them better, you find you only <hi>caſt Pearls before Swine,</hi> and
that there is more danger of getting hurt by them, than of doing them good, it
is fit that you deal roundly and plainly with them, and that you let them know,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:94705:54"/> that ſo long as they are no better, you deſire to be
excuſed, if you do not keep company with them. Tho' plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is very
neceſſary in this caſe, yet it is fit that it be tempered with all the
diſcretion and ſweetneſs that's poſſible, otherwiſe it may do more
hurt than good. Endeavour to make ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſenſible that you are
only an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to their Vices, and that as for their Perſons you will be
always ready to do them all good Offices.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> As you ought carefully to avoid the
company of thoſe who are Prophane and Atheiſtical Perſons, ſo it is
your Intereſt, as well as Duty, to viſit thoſe who are good and
Religious. <hi>They who feared the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi, Chap.</hi>
3.16.) <hi>ſpake often one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> When you have the opportunity of
enjoying the company of ſuch Perſons, make the beſt uſe of it that you
can. <hi>Conſider one another to provoke unto love, and to good works,</hi>
Heb. 10.24. <hi>Exhort one another daily,</hi> Heb. 3.13. Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, comfort,
and, in a friendly and loving manner, reprove one another, as there is need.
Make uſe of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Counſel and Advice, in any thing that is doubtful
and difficult. By all <pb n="103" facs="tcp:94705:54"/> diſcreet and prudent ways,
endeavour to learn ſome good and uſeful thing from good and wiſe
Perſons, with whom you have occaſion to converſe. <hi>Counſel in the
heart of a man,</hi> ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, is as deep waters; but a man of
underſtanding draws it out,</hi> Prov. 20.5. <hi>Counſel,</hi> that is, a
skill and dexterity to give good Advice and Counſel, and to talk of things
which tend to make men wiſer and better. This <hi>in the heart of a</hi>
wiſe <hi>man is like deep waters,</hi> that is, it makes no great noiſe
(the wiſeſt men being alſo the modeſteſt) and is not come at without
ſome pains, and ſome prudent Arts and Methods: <hi>But a man of
underſtanding draws it out,</hi> that is, by diſcreet and ſeaſonable
que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and other fit ways, he gives his wiſe Friend an opportunity to
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to communicate his thoughts, and to diſcover his wiſdom and
expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
                     <p>Beware leſt in good Company your Diſcourſe vaniſh
into air and ſmoak; leſt it be too trifling, and about things vain and
impertinent. <hi>Let your words be ſeaſoned with ſalt, miniſtring grace
to the bearers,</hi> Col. 4.6. Endeavour to receive benefit from the Society of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:94705:55"/> thoſe who are good and wiſe, and to do them good,
ſo far as you can, by your Society. <hi>As every Man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the
Gift,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter, even ſo Miniſter the ſame one to
another, as good Stewards of the manifold Grace of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.10.</p>
                     <p>It is true, it is not only lawful, but ſometimes very
convenient and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when virtuous and excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons meet
together, that they recreate and divert themſelves a little by
chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and innocent mirth, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their minds may be made more
fit for ſerious and ſacred things. Such is the ſtate and condition of
Man, while in the body, that his Soul cannot be always employed about thoſe
things which are of a Divine and Spiritual Nature: This vigour and ſtrength
of Soul is not, perhaps, attained to by any on this ſide the Grave. However,
our care muſt be, that the bent and inclination of our Hearts be toward
thoſe things that are good and uſeful. This muſt be our buſineſs, our
way, and courſe, <hi>to be good,</hi> and <hi>to do good:</hi> And as for our
Recreations and Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they muſt only be ſubſervient to the
other.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="105" facs="tcp:94705:55"/>
                        <note place="margin">6. Time to be
redeemed from worldly Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>
                        <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Redeem time from
your ordinary cares and worldly buſineſs, that you may do ſome great good
for the glory of God, and benefit of Mankind.</p>
                     <p>In the ordinary courſe of your Lives you muſt mind the
buſineſs of your Calling, according to your ſettled and uſual Method:
But then you are ſtill to remember, to let the concerns of your Soul take
place and be preferred. <hi>Firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God, and his
Righteouſneſs,</hi> Mat. 6.33.</p>
                     <p>At ſome times it is fit to deny your ſelves in the
affairs and concerns of this Life, to leave off your ordinary work and labour,
when your great Lord and Maſter affords you ſome extraordinary opportunity
for doing good to your Chriſtian Brother, or to your own Souls: Then you
muſt ſell things of leſſer value, that you may buy time for doing that
which will make you rich in the true Riches; that you may edifie your Brother,
and build up your ſelves in true Virtue.</p>
                     <p>The great matter is to know when you are to do ſo. You
muſt not every time when a ſudden thought ariſeth in <pb n="106" facs="tcp:94705:56"/> your mind, moving you to leave your Plough, or your Trade and
Calling, and to give up your ſelves to ſome Acts of Religion and Devotion;
you muſt not, I ſay, preſently ſet on this the ſtamp or ſeal of a
Divine Inſpiration, and a Call from Heaven. This, if not taken heed to, may
lead you into great miſtakes and errours, and very dangerous deluſions.
Sometimes Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, or other bodily Diſtempers, may give occaſion to a
great many warm fancies and imaginations: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you are not to follow
thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate motions and inclinations, if you are not ſome other way
determined thereto, by ſome concurring evidence of the hand of God. For
Example, if, when you are moved in your own mind to do ſome very good and
pious work, there happen about the ſame time an outward Call to do the ſame
thing, you may conclude there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what extraordinary in this to
deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine you. By an outward Call, I do not mean any extraordinary Voice from
Heaven: That's not to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but a Call by ſome good, wiſe, and
diſcreet Perſon, who unexpected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires and invites you to do that, 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:94705:56"/> which before his ſpeaking of it to you, you found your
own heart moved and inclined to. In which caſe you have a very mighty
encouragement, both from the goodneſs and uſefulneſs of the thing it
ſelf, and from the Call and invitation which you have had from another, of
whoſe Wiſdom and Piety you are ſufficiently aſſured. Tho' there be no
more but this Call from Man, it is of great weight to move you, and to
determine you in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to redeem your time from your ordinary labour,
when there is ſome extraordinary occaſion of doing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for the
honour of God, or the good of Men. Thus if at any time you are invited to
comfort one that is in any great trouble of Body or Mind, or in any other great
diſtreſs and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; if there be any thing in your power to do for the
comfort and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of ſuch a Perſon, you ought to ſhew your
readineſs to do your utmoſt for his help and ſupport. You know not but
the Lord may make uſe of you (however weak and unfit you may think your
ſelves) to ſerve the deſigns of his Mercy and Love. Likewiſe, if you
are called to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile <pb n="108" facs="tcp:94705:57"/> thoſe that are at variance; to
ſee if you can awaken a Perſon from his ſin and folly, eſpecially when
the Lord's hand is upon him; to give your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Advice in ſome
extraordinary caſe, where it is judged needful for you ſo to do: In theſe
and the like caſes you ought chearfully to Sacrifice your private gain and
advantage, and to let your leſſer cares give place to thoſe of a more
publick and conſiderable Nature.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things you are only to do, ſo far as the
neceſſity of your own oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions will permit. They who are ſettled in a
Calling, and have a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, are under a very ſtrict obligation to take care
of their Family, and to mind their Calling and Employment; they muſt not
neglect thoſe neceſſary Duties which God hath given them to do in their
ſeveral ſtations. The Scripture accounts them <hi>worſe than In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels,
who provide not for their Houſe, and thoſe of their own Family.</hi> But if
the Circumſtances of your affairs will permit you to comply with the
Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of performing ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent acts of Piety and Zeal, you ought
not to neglect them: God will not <pb n="109" facs="tcp:94705:57"/> fail plentifully to
reward your Love to him, and your Zeal for his Glory. 
<note place="margin">Short and fervent Ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, even in
Time of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</note>Tho' a great many can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpare
much time from their Worldly Buſineſs, for extraordinary Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of
Piety and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; yet there are none, who may not redeem ſome time from
their Buſineſs, by lifting up their Hearts, now and then, unto God, by
ſhort and fervent Ejaculatory Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or Thankſgivings, by earneſt
deſires and breathings, by humble Groans and ſecret Sighs, by ſerious
Acts of Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by frequent Acts of Love, of Hope, of Truſt and
Confidence, and of Reſignation to the divine Will. There is great
neceſſity for ſuch ſhort and fervent Acts of Devotion ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,
amidſt your affairs and buſineſs, conſidering the doubts and
difficulties, the hazards and dangers, and the ſnares and temptations, which
you are often expoſed to, as alſo the many unexpected and kind providences
you meet with, when you are employed in the Duties of your Calling. By
obſerving this Courſe, you do not hinder or interrupt your Buſineſs; on
the contrary, this is <pb n="110" facs="tcp:94705:58"/> the readieſt way to do it
ſucceſsfully, and moſt to your own comfort and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. We ſee
what <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did, when he waited upon <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> as his
Cup-bearer: The King having ſaid unto him, <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.4. <hi>For what
doſt thou make Requeſt,</hi> 'tis added, <hi>So I pray'd to the God of
Heaven.</hi> He knew how great need he had of God's Direction and
Aſſiſtance, and therefore, by a ſecret fervent Prayer, or Ejaculation,
he lifted up his Heart unto the Lord; And the Lord heard him, and both
aſſiſted him to preſent his Petition to the King, and inclined the
King's Heart to grant his Requeſt? <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
                     <p>Amongſt other Advantages which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Religious
Courſe, there is this; thereby you keep alive in your Hearts that ſacred
Fire, which was kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in the time of your more ſolemn Devotions. This is
the way <hi>to have your Converſation in Heaven, to walk with God, and to be
continually with him;</hi> this is to live like Citizens of the new
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> like Men whoſe Hearts are in Heaven, whoſe Treaſure
is there, and whoſe Love is fixt and ſettled on God and upon divine
things.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="111" facs="tcp:94705:58"/>
                        <note place="margin">7. Time to be
redeemed from Idleneſs.</note>
                        <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Redeem your time from
idleneſs, and an uſeleſs way of living in the World. A great many do not
waſte much time in ſleep, in dreſſing and adorning of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, in
eating and in drinking, in gaming, or in viſiting, and yet they waſte their
time: But how? In doing nothing, in entertaining themſelves with the vain
imaginations of their fooliſh minds, feeding on the Wind, purſuing dreams,
and catching at ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, building Caſtles in the Air, and ſporting
themſelves with their own vain conceits and fooliſh fancies. <hi>Their Eyes
are,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>in the ends of the Earth,</hi>
Prov. 17.24. They mind thoſe things moſt which concern them leaſt. They
buſie themſelves about what others ſay and do, but do nothing
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to any good purpoſe. Some Men are full of vain and uſeleſs
contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherewith they do indeed buſie themſelves: But to what end?
When all their deſigns and vain contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are accompliſhed, they are
but as ſo many Spiders Webs, only ſit to catch flyes. This is to be buſie
in Trifles, to be employed in doing as good as <pb n="112" facs="tcp:94705:59"/> nothing.
Thus there be ſome who pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue a ſtudious Life night and day, with a
wonderful diligence; but their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies being only in impertinent Books, and
about deſigns of no uſe, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of very bad uſe, they gain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
thereby; yea ſo far are they from reaping any benefit by their great pains
and labour, that they are unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loſers; they loſe their time, and
ſometimes they loſe their Wealth, and their Health, if not their Reaſon
and Underſtanding.</p>
                     <p>Conſider, <hi>firſt,</hi> how unworthy this ſort of
Life is of Men and of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? God hath made you to be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to
glorifie him, to do good in the World, to become daily more and more holy and
religious, <hi>to grow in grace, and to perfect holineſs in his fear;</hi>
and not to be like an uſeleſs Log, or an inſignificant Cypher; not to be
barren and unfruitful in his Vineyard. Strive therefore to live up to the end
and deſign of your being in the World, to improve your ſelves in Piety and
Virtue, to do ſomewhat that may be of real advantage to the Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
of others.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:94705:59"/>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider how
dangerous a thing it is to live an idle, vain, and unuſeful life. God hath
promiſed Men his protection, only when they are in the way of their Calling,
when they employ themſelves in that ſtate of life, wherein by his
Providence he hath ſettled them in the World. So the Pſalmiſt inſtructs
us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.11. <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee, to
keep thee in all thy ways;</hi> that is, in all honeſt and lawful
undertakings, and in all actions that belong to your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. So that if you
are idle, and give up your ſelves to a lazy and uſeleſs manner of living
in the World, doing nothing that's profitable to your ſelves or others, you
put your ſelves out of God's protection, and thereby you give the Devil
advantage over you, and you lay your ſelves open to all his Temptations. When
was it that <hi>David</hi> fell into thoſe two foul Sins of Adultery and
Murther? Was it not, when he yielded, for a ſhort time, to eaſe, and liv'd
idly at home? And if ſo excellent and holy a Perſon, was ſo ſoon
corrupted by Eaſe and Idleneſs, have you not great Reaſon to avoid this
Vice, which is deſervedly called, <pb n="114" facs="tcp:94705:60"/> 
                        <hi>The Mother of all
Evils, and the Step-Dame of all Virtues?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider that the end of this idle and
uſeleſs life is very ſad. <hi>Caſt the unprofitable Servent into utter
darkneſs, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth, Math.</hi> 25.30.
Not only ſhall wicked Servants be caſt into utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but alſo
unprofitable Servants, <hi>who hide their Talents in a Napkin;</hi> that is,
who do not employ to any good purpoſe thoſe Gifts which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows upon
them, <hi>who ſtand idle all the day long in the Vineyard.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">8. Time to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed in ſacred
performances, by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in the beſt manner.</note>
                        <hi>Eighthly,</hi>
Redeem time in your ſacred and religious Duties, and Performances, by
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to do them in the beſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteſt manner you can. When
you read, and pray, and meditate, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your ſelves, and hear the word
of God preached, and ſing his praiſes, and partake of the Holy Sacrament,
and perform other acts of Religion and Piety, in a lifeleſs, dull,
unconcerned and formal manner, you loſe your time; and therefore when by due
reflection upon your ways, you find that you do <pb n="115" facs="tcp:94705:60"/> ſo,
endeavour afterwards to redeem it, by greater watchfulneſs and
ſeriouſneſs; otherwiſe you may go on a great while in a courſe of
Devotion to very little purpoſe, if you do not ſtir up your ſelves to do
the beſt that's in your power to do, by God's help.</p>
                     <p>Thus when you find that you have read the Word of God in a
careleſs and negligent manner, without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering whoſe Word it is, and
for what end it is written, and without thoſe diſpoſitions of mind that
are neceſſary; you muſt afterwards endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the time, by
being more careful to read that Sacred Book with greater Reverence and
Seriouſneſs, and with greater Pleaſure and Delight. Pray to God more
heartily, for the direction and aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate
more attentively on what you read, and lay it up in your hearts, that it may be
always in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for your uſe, as the rule of your lives.</p>
                     <p>If you find that you have loſt your time in Prayer, by not
making your Addreſſes to God with a deep humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and reverence, with
unfeigned Faith, and fervent Love, and with <pb n="114" facs="tcp:94705:61"/> great
earneſtneſs, ſincerity, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity; endeavour afterwards to pray
with all poſſible humility and reverence, with greater faith and
confidence, and with a mighty earneſtneſs and ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Spirit: Study to
have your Souls poſſeſſed with a deeper ſenſe of your wants and
neceſſities, that you may beg ſupplies of all needful things from him who
can help you to the utmoſt. Be more ſenſible of the greatneſs of your
ſins, and of the many hainous ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations that attend them, that you may
make humble confeſſion of them with true ſorrow and contrition.
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the danger to which your Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, or Formality and
Lukewarmneſs in Religious Duties do expoſe you, that you may with great
integrity and uprightneſs of Soul, make your Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to <hi>the
Searcher of Hearts, and Tryer of the Reins,</hi> who takes pleaſure in the
hearty and chearful ſervices of thoſe who draw near unto him. Be
poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with more lively impreſſions of the Divine Power and
Greatneſs, of the Juſtice, Holineſs, Goodneſs, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and
Faithfulneſs of God, that the ſenſe thereof may make you adore him, and
call upon him in ſuch a <pb n="115" facs="tcp:94705:61"/> manner as is ſuitable to ſo
Glorious a Majeſty.</p>
                     <p>If you find that the time you have ſet apart for
Self-Examination has been loſt, by a negligent performance of this Duty, by
your not being in good earneſt, when you pretended to call your ſelves to
an account: Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to redeem the time, by ſearching your hearts, and
enquiring into your ways with greater care and exactneſs. Examine and try
your ſelves, as in the ſight of God, as Men that are in good earneſt to
ſave their Souls from Everlaſting Condemnation. Deal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially with your
ſelves; do not extenuate your own faults, but aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate them by all juſt
and fit conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: Endeavour to be deeply touch'd with hearty
Contrition and real Grief and Sorrow for them; let your Repentance in all
regards be more ſincere, and unfeigned, and your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and
Reſolutions more ſtrong and ſteady.</p>
                     <p>If you find that you have reflected on God's Mercies and
Favours to you, without that grateful ſenſe which you ought to have had
thereof, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making ſuitable returns, ſo far as 
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:94705:62"/> you were able by his Grace, for his great and
undeſerved goodneſs; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour afterwards to employ your thoughts on ſo
delightful a ſubject, as is the Divine Love and Goodneſs, with greater
pleaſure, and with a more live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſe thereof than you have been wont.
Let the conſideration of the love and goodneſs of God, powerfully move you,
and prevail with you to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which may teſtifie the reality of your
gratitude, ſomewhat that may be of real benefit to the Souls or Bodies of
others.</p>
                     <p>If you find that you have been very formal and careleſs in
performing what relates to the publick Worſhip, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to redeem the
time, by being more ſincere and devout. For Example, if you have heard the
Word of God read and preached, in a trifling and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned manner, without
thoſe diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mind which were requiſite in a Chriſtian
Hearer, and in an humble Diſciple of Jeſus Chriſt; if you have attended
on ſuch occaſions, more out of compliance with Cuſtom, and the Example of
others, than out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and from Principles of true Religion and
Devotion: Conſider that <pb n="119" facs="tcp:94705:62"/> this is to loſe time, and,
under an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Religion, to remain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing of it in
reality. You muſt therefore afterwards endeavour to hear the Word of God in
another manner, to wit, as the Law and Rule of your Lives, as that which is
given you of God to make you wiſe and good, and to fit you for everlaſting
Happineſs and Glory; you muſt, <hi>as new born Babes, deſire the
ſincere Milk of the Word, that your Souls may grow thereby.</hi> You muſt
hear it with great reverence and attention, and with humble and tractable
minds; you muſt ſtudy to have it ingrafted in your Hearts, that it may
abide there as a Scion in a ſtock, and may grow and bear fruit unto
everlaſting life. You muſt reflect on what you hear; when you leave the
Church, you muſt not lay aſide all further thinking on what has been read
or preached to you; you are to talk a little with your own hearts about thoſe
things, and to call to mind any thing you heard, which tends to make you
wiſer and better: Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to have it deeply imprinted on your Souls, that
it may prove unto <pb n="120" facs="tcp:94705:63"/> you <hi>the Power of God unto
Salvation, the ſavour of life unto life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If you find that you have been too often guilty of ſinging
the Praiſes of God with your mouths only, without any melody in your Hearts,
without any real ſenſe of the greatneſs and power, of the kindneſs and
love, of the patience and long-ſuffering, of the truth and faithfulneſs of
him whom you praiſe and celebrate: Endeavour to be more devout and ſerious
in that part of Worſhip; ſing unto God, not only with your Voice, but with
your Heart, which is the chief thing that God looks to. Study to raiſe your
Souls to him, as well as to lift up your Voices, when you ſing his praiſes.
Stir up all within you to bleſs his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name, <hi>who forgiveth all your
Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and healeth all your diſeaſes, who crowneth you with loving
kindneſs and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies,</hi> who prevents you every Morning, and
follows you all the day long, with many ſignal inſtances of his Fatherly
care and love, giving you richly all things to enjoy for life and
godlineſs.</p>
                     <p>If you find that you joyn in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers without
any due Senſe of <pb n="121" facs="tcp:94705:63"/> God upon your Souls, and without any
real impreſſion of thoſe things to which you ſay <hi>Amen;</hi> if you
find that you repeat ſome words as do others, but in the mean time your minds
are buſie in purſuing ſhadows, in thinking of your Trades, your Sports
and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be aſhamed that you do thus loſe your
precious time, that you are guilty of ſuch trifling in the moſt ſerious
and ſacred action: Endeavour to be more affected with a right ſenſe about
what, you do, that you may offer up unto God <hi>the Sacrifices of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and
contrite Hearts,</hi> that you may <hi>pour out your Hearts before him,</hi>
and may worſhip him with all your Soul and Mind. Bid farewel to your World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Cares, and to your Pleaſures and Vanities, when you come into his
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, to pay your homage to him. Serve him with your beſt affections,
with the ſtrength and vigour of your deſires, and with all your power and
might. If you do this, you may then expect, with great aſſurance and
confidence, that God will give ear unto you, and <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your longing
Souls with good things,</hi> he will make you <hi>taſte and ſee how good he
is.</hi> But if you pray without <pb n="122" facs="tcp:94705:64"/> being in good earneſt,
your Sacrifices will be an abomination to him, he will not regard your Prayers,
nor take any notice of you: <hi>He will anſwer you according to the multitude
of your Idols.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If you find that you loſe time by your communicating in a
careleſs and formal manner, without conſidering the end and deſign of
that holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and without endeavouring to prepare your ſelves as
you ought to do, that you may eat and drink wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily at the Table of the Lord;
ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to redeem this loſs, by partaking of this Sacrament for the time to
come in a more devout and religious manner: Be careful to approach with greater
love and gratitude unto the Table of your Lord, who not only allows you to
come, but kindly and lovingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites and encourages you to do ſo. Come with
your Souls burning with love to him who dyed for you, and who appointed you
this Sacrament, that therein you might remember his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful love, and his
aſtoniſhing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and mercy, which he hath teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in laying
down his life for ſinners, that he might purchaſe to them ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting 
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:94705:64"/> Life and Glory, even to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as repent and believe
the Goſpel. Come with your Hearts deeply wounded and pierced with ſorrow
for your ſins and follies, which were the cauſe of ſo ſhameful, ſo
painful, and ſo curſed a death to your deareſt Lord and Saviour. Come
with your Souls full of ſincere and hearty purpoſes and reſolutions of
being new Creatures, not to live any more unto your ſelves, or unto the
World, but to him who dyed for you. Come with your Souls likewiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged
with thoughts of kindneſs, and unfeigned Charity to all Men, with your minds
delivered from all bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and wrath, from all malice and envy, that you
may eat and drink at this Feaſt of Love, with ſutable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of
univerſal Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Come with a great deſire to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſtrength
from <hi>the God of your Salvation,</hi> that you may be able <hi>to fight the
good fight of Faith,</hi> and may at laſt <hi>lay hold on Eternal
Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In this manner you ought to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to redeem the time,
by doubling your care and diligence, in all thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion, in the
performance <pb n="124" facs="tcp:94705:65"/> whereof you have been formerly faulty and
defective.</p>
                     <p>Thus you are to do likewiſe in every other Action which
you perform to the glory of God. When you find that you have been too formal
and careleſs in what you have done and ſaid for God; for Example, in
admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing others, in inſtructing them, in reproving them, in comforting
them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> endeavour to redeem time, by doing thoſe things with
greater ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and zeal, with a more pure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Glory of God,
with a greater deſire to approve your ſelves unto him, who gives you the
opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of doing ſomewhat for his Honour, and with greater Charity to
the Souls of Men.</p>
                     <p>Depend on God for a Bleſſing in all your endeavours, beg
of him that he would direct and aſſiſt you to do that which is good and
well pleaſing unto him; and that he would ſo diſpoſe the hearts of
thoſe whom you admoniſh, inſtruct, reprove, or comfort, that what you
ſpeak to them may not be loſt, but may have the deſired effect, for the
glory of God, and their happineſs and welfare.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="125" facs="tcp:94705:65"/>From what hath been ſaid, you may
ſee how you ought to redeem your time: The next thing which I propoſed to
ſpeak to, was, to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt to you ſome Conſiderations to excite you
to do ſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Some Motives to excite you to do theſe things.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1. Motive, from the ſhortneſs of your
Time.</note>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider how ſhort your time is. Your life is
compared to a <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, which appears for a little time, and then
vaniſheth away, Jam.</hi> 4.14. It makes a little ſhew and appearance for a
while, and then it is gone. It is compared to a <hi>Poſt,</hi> to the
<hi>Swift Ships,</hi> and to the <hi>Eagle that haſteth to the Prey, Job</hi>
9.25,26. And to the <hi>Wind,</hi> and to a <hi>Weaver</hi>'s <hi>ſhuttle,
Job</hi> 7.6,7. All which Compariſons ſerve to expreſs how ſhort and
ſwift our time is, how ſuddenly it flies away and is gone. <hi>Man that is
born of a Woman</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 14.1.) <hi>is of few
days.</hi> And <hi>Jacob,</hi> (when he was a great deal older than Men live to
be now, even 130 years old) told <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Few 
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:94705:66"/> and evil have the days of the years of my life been.</hi>
What are 40, or 60, or 80 years, when a Man lives ſo long, and looks back
upon them all? They appear to him but like a <hi>Shadow,</hi> or as a
<hi>Dream,</hi> or like a <hi>Tale that is told.</hi> Ought not this to move
you to be good Husbands of your ſhort time? If it were in your own power to
diſpoſe of it, according to your own humour and fancy, you might then be
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned to delay your great Work and Buſineſs till you thought good: But
now that it is not in your power to lengthen out your time one Minute, what a
madneſs is it for you to put off and neglect your greateſt and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
Concern? Therefore be ſo wiſe, as to make good uſe of your preſent
opportunities and occaſions of doing good, that you may <hi>work out your
Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with fear and trembling,</hi> and may <hi>make your calling and your
Election ſure. Work while the day laſts, for the night com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wherein you
cannot work.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If a Man who is guilty of Treaſon, or Rebellion againſt
his Prince, or of any other great Crime which deſerves death, were allowed a
few days to ſue out his Pardon, that he might ſecure <pb n="127" facs="tcp:94705:66"/>
his Life and Eſtate, would he not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove with great care and diligence that
little time? To be ſure he would not loſe one moment of it: And tho'
perhaps at other times, he was wont to give up himſelf to his pleaſures and
paſtimes, and to mind little elſe, but the gratifying his Luſts and
Paſſions, and his Vanity and Folly; yet now that his Life and Fortune lie
at the ſtake, you ſhould ſee ſuch a man changed in a moment: You
ſhould ſee him, with great application of mind, with the utmoſt diligence
imploying his time, running from place to place, from one perſon to another,
according as his great and important buſineſs and concern required. How
readily would ſuch a Perſon redeem his time, not only from Idleneſs, from
Gaming, from impertinent Viſits, and from dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and adorning of his
Body, and the like, but even from eating and drinking, and from his reſt and
repoſe in the night? The deſire of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his life would ſo fill
his thoughts, as to make him forget almoſt every thing elſe. What would you
think or ſay, if you ſhould ſee a man in ſuch circumſtances wholly
unconcerned and <pb n="128" facs="tcp:94705:67"/> careleſs, ſpending his time in
Gaming, or Idleneſs, in making impertinent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, in rioting and
drinking, and the like, and doing nothing at all to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his pardon, and to
ſecure his life and fortune? Doubtleſs you would look upon ſuch a man as
void of common underſtanding, fit only for <hi>Bedlam,</hi> or not worthy to
live, who knew no better to make uſe of his ſhort time, to preſerve his
life, which Nature teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all Men to do, by all honeſt and lawful
means.</p>
                     <p>It is eaſie for you to make appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of all this to
your ſelves. You are by your Sins Enemies to God, Rebels againſt your Lord
and King, whereby you are in danger of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death and deſtruction.
But God in his infinite mercy gives you time to ſue out your Pardon, which he
offers you upon the moſt juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable conditions; only
<hi>believe</hi> and <hi>repent,</hi> and you ſhall be ſaved; he will have
mercy upon you, and blot out your iniquities. Be therefore ſo wiſe, as to
husband well this ſhort time, which God beſtows on you for this purpoſe:
Redeem it as much as you can, from all vain and unneceſſary things, 
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:94705:67"/> that you may obtain forgiveneſs of Sins, and the
aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit, to enable you afterwards to walk in
new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life.</p>
                     <p>But if inſtead of minding this great and important concern
of your Souls, you give up your ſelves to ſin and folly, and indulge your
ſelves in your mad and wicked practices, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by provoke God yet more
and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, how juſt will your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Condemnation be? if
you will not be ſaved, if you will not turn to the Lord that you may live, if
you will not believe, repent, and amend; what remains? you ſhall certainly
dye, and be miſerable for ever. They that will not be happy, ſhall not be
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. <hi>The wrath of God ſhall abide upon them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2. Motive, from the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of your
Time.</note>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider that as your time is very ſhort,
ſo it is moſt uncertain. What do you know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Sun ſhall decline
leiſurely, or whether it may not go down ſuddenly, when you think it is not
yet come to the Noon-tide of the Day? You are not ſure to live till you come
to a good old Age. How many ſickneſſes <pb n="130" facs="tcp:94705:68"/> and
diſtempers, and how many ſudden accidents are there in the way, which may
ſhorten your day, and cauſe your Sun to ſet, when you think it ſhines
with its greateſt force and luſtre? Sometimes a Candle is blown out by the
Wind, or ſnufft out undeſignedly, when it is not yet half burnt. And ſo
the life of Man is often extinguiſhed by outward accidents, when by the
courſe of Nature, it might have been prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much further.</p>
                     <p>How many come forth into the World, and give great
appearances of making a very conſiderable figure in it, by their Wiſdom and
Sagacity, their good Conduct, and Addreſs, their Excellent Parts and uſeful
Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, their Courage and Valour, their Charming Eloquence, and clear and
diſtinct Reaſoning, or by their ſhining Piety and burning Zeal? But do
not you ſee how ſuddenly they are gone? they are hurried away by death, and
you neither ſee them nor hear of them any more.</p>
                     <p>There is nothing certain as to your time, but its
ſhortneſs and uncertainty. Nothing can ſecure you againſt an unexpected
blow by death, when God <pb n="131" facs="tcp:94705:68"/> ſees fit to give charge to the
King of Terrors to knock you down. Youth and ſtrength cannot do it; for how
many die <hi>when their Breaſts are full of milk, and their bones are
moiſtened with marrow?</hi> Too great abundance of Blood and Spirits doth
ſometimes oppreſs and ſtifle the life of Man.</p>
                     <p>Wealth and Riches cannot ſecure you: How many great and
wealthy men have been ſuddenly carried away as with a Flood, when their
Coffers were full of Silver and Gold, when they had all that heart could
wiſh? Even their Wealth proved the bait which allured idle, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, and
deſperate Perſons, to break into their Houſes, and rob them, not only of
their Treaſure, but of their Lives.</p>
                     <p>Greatneſs of Power and earthly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Dignity, are
not able to do it: Crowns and Scepters, Caſtles and Palaces, a wiſe
Council, and great Armies, are not able to protect Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, from the violent
and deſperate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of Men, who are prodigal of their lives. How many of
thoſe who have been moſt famous in the World for their Power and
Greatneſs, have been very unexpectedly removed by a <pb n="132" facs="tcp:94705:69"/>
violent and ſudden death? When they have been in their greateſt heighth, at
the very top of Earthly Felicity, and full of the deepeſt Projects and
Deſigns; when they made account to make the Earth, as it were, to tremble; to
humble and to mortifie their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to enlarge their own Dominions, or to
enſlave their Subjects, even then Death gave them a ſudden blow, and ſo
there was an end of them and their deſigns together.</p>
                     <p>But may not Wiſdom and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, great Learning,
and Skill in various Arts and Sciences, do ſomewhat to ſecure Men from the
ſudden blow of Death? No, all this cannot do it: We ſee even Wiſe Men
ſuddenly and unexpectedly removed from us by Death, as well as others. In the
midſt of their uſeful Studies, and excellent contrivances, and deſigns,
the King of Terrors puts a ſtop to them, and in the twinkling of an Eye they
are gone, and all their thoughts are laid aſleep. So vain a thing is Man, and
even the wiſeſt Man; and ſo uncertain is his time.</p>
                     <p>Conſider that Death can enter by a thouſand doors. Every
pore in your <pb n="133" facs="tcp:94705:69"/> Body is a Gate wide enough for Death to
enter in at. Do not you ſee what a ſmall thing makes way for Death? The
prick of a Thorn, or a Splinter of Wood does it ſometimes, by occaſioning a
Fever, or a Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene. How quickly are ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by violent and
unexpected Diſtempers, and ſometimes on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den are ſtruck dead, you
cannot tell how? Have not ſome dyed through an exceſs of joy, and others
through immoderate grief; ſome by exceſſive laughter, and others by too
much mourning and weeping? Some have died with a fright or ſudden fear:
ſome by the violence of their anger and wrath, and others by an exceſs of
Love. How many have been killed with over much care, and too great watching?
and others have occaſioned their own death by idleneſs, and too much
ſleep: Some have killed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with eating and drinking, and others
have done it by too great abſtinence and faſting. Have not ſome died
while they have been at Meals, by a Crumb, or a little Bone, or ſome ſuch
very ſmall matter? When they were thinking to repair their ſtrength, 
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:94705:70"/> and to fit themſelves for going on with their
buſineſs and work; that which they did to ſave and length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en out their
lives, did ſhorten them, and put an end to them. May not this inſtance
alone ſhew you the great uncertainty of your time, and how neceſſary it
is to redeem it?</p>
                     <p>But beſides all this, conſider that when you go abroad,
you are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from innumerable accidents. You may be killed by the
noiſome ſteams of the Earth, by ſome infectious quality in the Air, by
the Beaſts of the Field, by the teeth of mad Dogs, by the horns of enraged
Oxen, or by the heels of wild Horſes. You are likewiſe in danger from the
winged Creatures, the leaſt of whom have Weapons ſufficient to deſtroy
you, if God by his Power and Juſtice arm them againſt you.</p>
                     <p>How remarkable was the manner of the death of
<hi>Aeſchylus,</hi> an ancient Poet in <hi>Sicily,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Valer. Max.</hi> lib. 9. cap. 12.</note> who as he ſate in a
Sunny place without the Walls of the City, was killed by a Tortoiſe, which an
Eagle let fall on his head.</p>
                     <p>And no leſs memorable is the Story which is mentioned in
the Book of Martyrs, of one <hi>Burton,</hi> Bailiff of <hi>Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 
                        <pb n="135" facs="tcp:94705:70"/> in <hi>Linconſhire,</hi> who pretending to be a Friend
to the Reformation in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time; after the King's death began
to ſet up the Popiſh Maſs again, and would have beaten the Curate, if he
had not complied with his deſign: But ſee how the Lord's hand overtook him;
as he came riding from <hi>Fenbank</hi> one day, a Crow flying over his head,
let fall her Excrements upon his face, the noiſom ſcent whereof ſo
annoyed his ſtomach, that he never ceaſed vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting till he came home: And
after falling deadly ſick, would never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any meat, but vomited
ſtill, and complained of that ſtink, curſing the Crow that had poiſoned
him; and in a few days he died.</p>
                     <p>Beſides the danger you are in from unreaſonable
Creatures, are you not alſo ſometimes in hazard from Men, who are mad
either through the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper of their Brain, or through their violent Malice
and Envy? <hi>Let a Bear robbed of her Whelps</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>)
<hi>meet a Man rather than a Fool in his folly,</hi> Prov. 17.12. And not only
are your Lives in danger from unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures and from Men, but
likewiſe from the Spirits of Darkneſs, <pb n="136" facs="tcp:94705:71"/> unleſs
reſtrained by the mighty Power of God. Theſe are Enemies of great Power,
and of as great, yea greater Malice. But your heavenly Father keeps them as it
were in chains, and ſets bounds to their rage and fury, that they cannot hurt
you ſo much as in a hair of your head, without the Divine permiſſion.</p>
                     <p>But further; ſo uncertain is your time, that there is not
a ſtone, nor a block in your way, but it may be an occaſion of your
ſtumbling, and falling into the ſnares of Death. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when
there is no ſuch block in your way, you are not ſecure from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: One
foot may prove a ſtumbling-block to the other, and an occaſion of your
falling into the hands of Death. When you walk in the ſtreets either for
Buſineſs or Divertiſement, and have not the leaſt apprehenſion of any
danger, even then Death may hang over your Heads: Every Tile on the
Houſe-tops, may by its unexpected fall, as you paſs by, beat out your
Brains, and ſo put an end to all your Thoughts and Motions.</p>
                     <p>And more than all this; in how great danger are your Lives
from Fire, <pb n="137" facs="tcp:94705:71"/> and from Water, from Heat and Cold, from
Storms and Tempeſts, from Thunder and Lightning, and many other things, the
ſtroke whereof you cannot prevent nor foreſee? God hath in ſtore the
Sword, the Famine, and Peſtilence, and innumerable Judgments and Plagues,
whereby he can cut you off, and ſhorten your Lives.</p>
                     <p>When you are in your houſes, and think your ſelves in
ſafety, you know not but that Death is even there, and that your Grave is
ready for you: By a ſudden Wind, by an Earthquake, or by a decay in the
Foundation, or ſome other part of the Building, the Houſe may fall down
about your ears, and prove your burying place.</p>
                     <p>So true is it what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Eccl.</hi>
9.12. <hi>For Man alſo knoweth not his Time; as the Fiſhes that are taken
in an evil Net, and as the Birds that are caught in the Snare: So are the Sons
of Men ſnared in an evil Time, when it falleth ſuddenly upon them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>From all which you may conclude, that your time is the
moſt uncertain thing in the World. Ought you not therefore to make good uſe
of it while <pb n="138" facs="tcp:94705:72"/> it laſts, not knowing how ſoon and
ſuddenly it may be at an end?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">3. Motive, from the greatneſs and
difficulty of the work you have to do.</note>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider how
great and difficult a work you have to do; a work that requires a great part of
your time, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all your time. How hard is it to work out your
Salvation, to make your Calling and Election ſure; to ſtrive to enter in at
the ſtrait Gate; to be born again; to be made new Creatures; to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed
in the Spirit of your mind; to put off the works of darkneſs, and to put on
the armour of light; to add to your faith, virtue,; and to virtue, knowledge;
and to knowledge, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance; and to temperance, patience; and to patience,
godlineſs; and to godlineſs, brotherly kindneſs; and to brotherly
kindneſs, charity? To have the image of God renewed in your Souls; to be made
partakers of the Divine Nature, to eſcape the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are in the
World through luſt; to be conformed to the Example of your Bleſſed Lord
and Maſter, in thoſe Virtues wherein you ought to imitate him; to learn of
him who <pb n="139" facs="tcp:94705:72"/> was meek and lowly; to go about as he did, doing
good to the Souls and Bodies of Men; to be zealous for God; and holy as he who
called you is holy in all manner of Converſation?</p>
                     <p>How great a work is it to overcome your ſelves? To become
vile and baſe in your own eyes, to think meanly of your ſelves, and to be
willing that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould think ſo of you too; to be content with every
ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, wherein God does by his Providence place you;
to bear wrongs and injuries with meekneſs and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; not to be overcome
with evil, but to overcome evil with good; to mortifie your ſinful deſires
and ſenſual appetites; to crucifie the fleſh with the affections and
luſts; to purifie your ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and
ſpirit; to cleanſe your Hearts from all manner of wickedneſs, that they
may be fit Temples for the Spirit of God to dwell in; to govern your eyes, that
you may not thereby betray your Souls into the hands of your Enemies; to govern
your Lips, to take heed to your ways, that you offend not with your Tongue; to
put away from you all ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, flattery, and diſſimulation, all evil
ſpeaking, whiſpering, and backbiting, <pb n="140" facs="tcp:94705:73"/> all fooliſh
talking and jeſting, which are not convenient; to be ſober and temperate in
all things; to be juſt and ſincere in all your dealings, doing to others
what you would have them do to you?</p>
                     <p>How great a work is it to overcome the World? to deſpiſe
its Pomps and Vanities, not to be allured and charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by its ſmiles, nor yet
frighted and caſt down by its frowns; not to ſuffer your ſelves to be
poſſeſſed with the love of Riches; to entertain juſt and fit opinions
of the things of this World; to conſider them as vain, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, and
unſatisfactory enjoyments, which are not capable to make you happy, which are
only ſo far to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, as they are neceſſary in order to your
accommodation and more eaſie ſubſiſtence in the World? How hard is it
to overcome the temptations of earthly pleaſure and outward delights, and not
to ſuffer your minds to be too far tranſported by the love of them; but to
uſe even the moſt innocent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures with great moderation, leſt they
lead the Soul Captive, and render it unfit for the true pleaſures? How hard
is it to live in the World as Pilgrims <pb n="141" facs="tcp:94705:73"/> and Strangers
ought to do, to paſs through this Wilderneſs without much regarding it, but
fixing your eyes on the happy Land, the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> which you
ought to look on as your only Country? How hard is it to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the danger
of the evil Manners and Cuſtoms which are in the World? The many temptations
which you have to vanity and folly, to pride and paſſion, to gluttony and
drunkenneſs, to luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſenſuality, and to other Vices, by the bad
Examples of your Friends, Neighbours, and other Acquaintan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</p>
                     <p>How great and difficult a work is it to reſiſt the
Devil, to quench his fiery darts, to reject his ſuggeſtions, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
his wiles and ſtratagems, to watch againſt all his aſſaults, and
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly to oppoſe his temptations, that you may overcome him and
tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over him? Now, this is the work you have to do: <hi>For we wreſtle
not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12.) <hi>againſt fleſh and
blood, but againſt principalities, againſt powers, againſt the rulers of
the darkneſs of this world, againſt ſpiritual wickedneſs in high
places.</hi> How hard and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a Warfare muſt it needs be, that 
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:94705:74"/> makes it neceſſary for you <hi>to take the whole
Armour of God, that you may be able to withſtand in the evil day, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
done all, to ſtand?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How hard a work is it to read, and hear, and meditate, to
examine your ſelves, to pray to God, and to praiſe him, to partake of the
holy Sacrament, and to perform all other Acts of Devotion and Piety, as you
ought to do?</p>
                     <p>How great a work is it to love God above all things, to love
him with all your Soul and Heart, and with all your ſtrength and might, and
to keep your ſelves in the Love of God, that it may be in you a powerful
Spring and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple unto all good actions, that you may be thereby ſweetly
conſtrained to do and to ſuffer whatever is his holy Will and
Pleaſure?</p>
                     <p>Is it not a great work to perform aright all thoſe Duties
which you are bound to do in your ſeveral relations and capacities? To
inſtruct, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, to reprove, and to comfort o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to do every
thing you can for the good of Mens Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? <hi>Let no Man</hi>
(ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.24.) <hi>ſeek his own, but every
Man anothers wealth.</hi> And, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.5. <pb n="143" facs="tcp:94705:74"/>
                        <hi>Charity ſeeketh not its own,</hi> that is, not only its own; it ſeeketh
not its own to the prejudice of another; but it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to promote the
happineſs and welfare of others. The charitable Perſon hath an eye to the
good and benefit of other Men, as well as his own gain and advantage.</p>
                     <p>And beſides all this, you ought to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ave ſo much Zeal for the Glory of
God, and the good of Souls, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to do ſomewhat which may
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ave a laſting effect and
influence not only in the preſent time, but in the time to come: You ought to
contrive by all means to propagate Religion, to do ſomewhat which may bear
fruit for the honour of your Maker and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, when you are laid in the
Grave.</p>
                     <p>From all which you may ſee what a great and difficult work
you have to do in the World, and how great need you have to redeem time, and to
loſe as little of it as is poſſible. How ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary is it for you to
begin your work betimes, and to be conſtant in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of it, <hi>In
the Morning to ſow your Seed, and in the Evening not to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold 
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:94705:75"/> your hand?</hi> What a madneſs is it to have your work
to begin when your time is almoſt at an end, when there are but a few ſands
in your Glaſs? You who have ſo long a Race to run, and ſo much bad Way to
paſs through, and who are ſo weak, and have ſo little ſtrength to
ſtir one foot, to do, or ſay, or think any thing that is good, have you not
great need to ſet out in good time, and to continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied in your
courſe, all the day, that you may at laſt receive the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious prize?
Ought you not <hi>(forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe things that are behind, and reaching
forth unto thoſe things which are before) to preſs towards the mark, for
the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 3.13,14.
Ariſe therefore from your ſloth and lazineſs, <hi>and run and be not
weary; and walk, and do not faint.</hi> Pray to God to hold up your goings in
his paths, that your footſteps may not ſlide, to ſtrengthen your weak
hands, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm your feeble knees, to draw you that you may run after him,
and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him fully. Beg of him, that he would be at your right hand to
direct <pb n="145" facs="tcp:94705:75"/> and defend you, that he would perfect his
ſtrength in your weakneſs, and would give you in all things both to will
and to do, according to his good pleaſure; that when you meet with enemies in
your way, he would teach your hands to war, and your fingers to fight; and that
his Grace may be ſufficient for you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">4. Motive, from the Account you muſt
give how you ſpend your Time.</note>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider that you
muſt give an account of your time, how you ſpend and employ it. God hath
appointed a day wherein he will judge the World in Righteouſneſs, by his
Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, who is to come from Heaven very unexpectedly and
ſuddenly, in a moſt dreadful and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, with Power and great
Glory, in the Clouds of Heaven, in flaming fire, with ten thouſands of his
holy Angels, with a ſhout, with the voice of the Archangel, and with the
Trump of God. He ſhall ſend his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and they ſhall gather together
his Elect from the four Winds, from one end of Heaven to the other. The Throne
ſhall be ſet, and all Nations <pb n="146" facs="tcp:94705:76"/> ſhall be gathered
before him. The Books ſhall be opened, and the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of darkneſs
ſhall be brought to light; the counſels of the heart ſhall be made
manifeſt; and every work ſhall be brought into Judgment, with every
ſecret thing, whether it be good or bad. There ſhall be no need of
Witneſſes againſt the guilty, nor of Racks and Tortures to extort their
Confeſſions: Every Man's own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall be inſtead of a
thouſand Witneſſes. Then ſhall the Judge paſs Sentence on every Man
according to his works. The righteous ſhall be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and ſhall
receive the reward of everlaſting Life and Glory: They ſhall be made
partakers of a Crown of Glory which fadeth not away, and of a Kingdom that
cannot be ſhaken. But the wicked ſhall be caſt into utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
where there is weeping and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of teeth, where the Worm dieth not, and
where the fire ſhall never be quenched: Where they ſhall continue for ever
deprived of the Favour and Love of God, and expoſed to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable
load of his anger and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="147" facs="tcp:94705:76"/>You profeſs to believe theſe
things, and therefore ought you not ſo to live, and ſo to husband your
time, that when the Judge cometh, he may not find you idle, nor doing ſuch
things as are to his diſhonour?</p>
                     <p>You may by the following Similitude, conceive ſomewhat
concerning the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent thoughts of good and bad Men, upon ſuch a ſudden
appearance of the Judge. Suppoſe a Prince going into a far Country, ſhould
call together his Servants, appointing them ſeverally their work till his
return (which he tells them will be unexpected) and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing great rewards
of Houſes, and Lands, and honourable Employments, to the faithful and
obedient Servants; but threatning ſevere puniſhments, and torments, and a
terrible death, to the unfaithful and diſobedient. If after his departure
ſome of the Servants mind their buſineſs, obſerving, as well as they
can, what their Maſter requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to do: Others, without any regard to
his Commands, take no thought of their buſineſs, but are idle, <hi>and eat
and drink with the drunken, and ſmite their fellow Servants,</hi> and 
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:94705:77"/> both by their words and deeds diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their Lord.
You may eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine how differently theſe Servants will be affected
when he returns ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and unexpectedly. The good Servants will be glad
and rejoyce at his coming, and will meet him with great chearfulneſs and
confidence, as expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the accompliſhment of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and being
conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of having done their Duty ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and
faithfully, of having car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried themſelves, as they ought to have done, during
his abſence: But the naughty and wicked Servants, muſt needs be filled with
ſhame and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon the Coming of their Lord, ſo as not to be able
to look him in the face; There is no other thing which they can do, but to
endeavour to fly from his preſence, that they may not fall under the weight
of his terrible diſpleaſure.</p>
                     <p>In this manner our Lord and Maſter Jeſus, before he left
the World, gave Rules and Commands to his Servants how to employ themſelves,
and what to do till his return. He promiſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to all who ſhould
believe and <pb n="149" facs="tcp:94705:77"/> obey; and threatned the unbelievers, and the
diſobedient with heavy Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and moſt dreadful Judgments. When he
comes again in the great Day to judge the World, the godly ſhall meet him
with great hope and aſſurance, of obtaining <hi>the end of their Faith,
even the Salvation of their Souls.</hi> But the wicked and unbelievers ſhall
be full of horrour and confuſion, and ſhall cry, tho' in vain, to the
Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to fall on them, to hide them from the face of their Judge, who will
be a conſuming Fire to all the workers of iniquity, and will in no wiſe
clear the guilty.</p>
                     <p>Now do you deſire heartily and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to eſcape
everlaſting Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and to obtain a glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the Day of
your Accounts? Then you muſt ſtudy to redeem the time, and to make uſe of
all oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of doing good: You muſt not be ſlothful in your great
buſineſs, but <hi>fervent in Spirit, ſerving the Lord, knowing that your
labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You ſee how the Men of the World beſtir themſelves,
when there is but a <pb n="150" facs="tcp:94705:78"/> ſmall appearance and probability of
gain and advantage. The Merchants make uſe of every favourable oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
to buy and ſell; they go early to Market, that they may not loſe a good
occaſion; and yet after all, they may be, and are frequently diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,
and make a very bad bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. But the Chriſtian, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deems his time to buy
Wiſdom, is ſure to find it. <hi>They who ſeek me early, ſhall find
me,</hi> Prov. 8.17.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Mariners</hi> wait for a favourable Gale, a fair and
ſeaſonable Wind, to go to Sea: And when it blows accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to their
wiſhes they are ſure not to loſe one moment. Their deſire of gain, and
their hopes of a proſperous Voyage, makes them venture. And yet after all,
they may, and often do ſuffer ſhipwrack, and loſe their goods and their
lives too. But the Chriſtian who redeems his time, is in no ſuch danger; he
is ſure to arrive ſafely at the Harbour of everlaſting Reſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all
the ſtorms and tempeſts, which he meets with in the boiſterous Sea of
this World.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="151" facs="tcp:94705:78"/>The <hi>Husbandmen</hi> wait for a good
ſeaſon to Plough, and Sow, and to do all other things belonging to their
Employment; and when the time is favourable, they are ſure to make uſe of
it. The deſire and hopes they have of a Harveſt, of a fruitful Crop,
quickens their endeavours, and excites their induſtry. And yet after all,
they may be diſappointed. Their Corn may be drowned by violent Rains, or
ſcorched and burnt up with violent Heat, or eaten up and conſumed by
Inſects, Fowls, or Beaſts. But the Chriſtian who <hi>ſows in tears,
ſhall reap in joy,</hi> Pſal. 126.5,6.</p>
                     <p>You ſee that Men, who run a Race, ſtrive with great
earneſtneſs to gain the Prize, to obtain that, which oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is of no
very great value. And yet ſome of thoſe who run come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and are
diſappointed of their hopes. But the Chriſtian <hi>runs not
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly;</hi> he is ſure to <hi>obtain not a corruptible Crown, but an
incorruptible,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.25.</p>
                     <p>Again, you ſee that Men who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege a City or a
Caſtle, wait for all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and are ſure not to neglect 
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:94705:79"/> a favourable occaſion of making an Aſſault, and
ſurpriſing the Enemy The hopes of getting rich Spoils, of gaining Honour
and Renown, makes them reſolute and valiant. And yet it often happens, that
they loſe their lives in the Attempt; or are taken Captive by thoſe whom
they did hope to overcome and ſubdue. But he who <hi>fights the good fight of
Faith,</hi> is ſure <hi>to lay hold on eternal Life.</hi> He who fights under
Chriſt's Banner, and who has him for his Captain, is ſure to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the
Victory over all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note>I ſhall
conclude this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with what is written by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2
<hi>Epiſt. Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10,11, &amp;c. <hi>The day of the
Lord will come as a thief in the night, in the which the Heaven ſhall paſs
away with a great noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, the
Earth alſo, and the works that are therein, ſhall be burnt up. Seeing then
that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved, what manner of Perſons
ought you to be in all holy Converſation and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; Looking for, and
haſtening unto the coming of the day of God, wherein <pb n="153" facs="tcp:94705:79"/>
the Heavens being on fire ſhall be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the Elements ſhall
melt with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent heat? Nevertheleſs we, according to his promiſe, look
for new Heavens, and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
Wherefore (beloved) ſeeing that ye look for ſuch things, be diligent, that
ye may be found of him in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:94705:80"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94705:80"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF Advice to Children.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Introduction. 1</item>
               <item>1. Duty of Children, to Honour their Parents. And how they
are are to Honour them. 2 
<p>The Poverty of Parents does not exempt Children from this
Duty. 6</p> 
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:94705:81"/>Againſt thoſe who diſhonour their Parents.
7</p>
               </item>
               <item>2. Duty of Children, to obey their Parents, and hearken to
their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. 10 
<p>Againſt ſtubborn and diſobedient Children. 14</p>
               </item>
               <item>3. Duty, to be faithful to their Parents, and not to
diſpoſe of their goods without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. 16 
<p>Againſt unfaithful and treacherous Children. 18</p>
               </item>
               <item>4. Duty of Children, to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by their Parents as to
their Calling. 20 
<p>Againſt Children who neglect this Duty. 22</p>
               </item>
               <item>5. Duty of Children, not to ſuffer themſelves to be
beſtowed in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage againſt their Parents will. 23 
<p>Againſt thoſe Children who neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this Duty.
26</p>
               </item>
               <item>6. Duty of Children, to ſubmit to <pb facs="tcp:94705:81"/> their
Parents Reproofs, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenings. 27 
<p>Againſt Rebellious Children. 28</p>
               </item>
               <item>7. Duty of Children, to love their Parents; and how they are
to expreſs their Love. 31 
<p>Againſt unkind and unnatural Children. 35</p>
               </item>
               <item>8. Duty of Children, to pray for their Parents. 36 
<p>Againſt Curſers of Parents. 37</p>
               </item>
               <item>The Duties of Children towards their Deceaſed Parents. 38 
<list>
                     <item>1. Duty, they ought to bury them decently. 38</item>
                     <item>2. Duty, to fulfill their laſt Will. 40</item>
                     <item>3. Duty, to call to mind their good Advices, and to
follow their good Examples. 40</item>
                     <item>4. Duty, to do what they can law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, to ſuppreſs
Evil Reports concerning them. 42</item>
                     <item>5. Duty, to retain a firm kindneſs for their Friends.
43</item>
                     <item>Againſt Children who neglect theſe Duties. 44</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:94705:82"/>Motives to excite Children to do theſe things.

<list>
                     <item>1. Motive, from the Authority of him who commands them to
do theſe things. 46</item>
                     <item>2. Motive, from the Promiſe made to thoſe who do
their Duty. 49</item>
                     <item>3. Motive, from the Example of our Bleſſed Maſter.
53</item>
                     <item>4. Motive, from the Examples of ſome Heathens.
56</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion, ſhewing how Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought to improve
what hath been ſaid. 60</item>
               <item>The Duties of Children to their Step-Parents. 70 
<p>Some Motives to ſtir up Children to be Dutiful to them.
72</p> 
                  <p>Againſt thoſe who are undutiful towards their
Step-Parents. 74</p>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:94705:82"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF The Diſcourſe about the Right Way of
Improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Time.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Introduction. 79</item>
               <item>The Text explained. 80</item>
               <item>How Time is to be redeemed. 
<list>
                     <item>1. Time is to be redeemed from ſleep. 82</item>
                     <item>2. It is to be redeemed from dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and adorning the
Body. 86</item>
                     <item>3. It is to be redeemed from eating and drinking.
90</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:94705:83"/>4. It is to be redeemed from gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
92</item>
                     <item>5. It is to be redeemed from viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 97</item>
                     <item>6. Time is to be redeemed from Worldly Buſineſs. 105 
<p>Short and ferv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt Ejaculations, ev'n in Time of Buſineſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended.
109</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. It is to be redeemed from idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 111</item>
                     <item>8. It is to be redeemed in ſacred and religious
Perfomrances, by doing them in the beſt manner. 114.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Some Motives to Excite you to do theſe things. 
<list>
                     <item>1. Motive, from the ſhortneſs of your Time.
125</item>
                     <item>2. Motive, from the uncertainty of your Time. 129</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:94705:83"/>3. Motive, from the greatneſs and
difficulty of the work you have to do. 138</item>
                     <item>4. Motive, from the account you muſt give how you
ſpend your Time. 145</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion. 152</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
